<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ, on his throne; not in popish secrets A prophecie of Christ, against his pretended presence in popish secrets; laid open in a sermon preached before his Maiestie at Wansted certaine yeares agoe, and since much inlarged, and (vpon request) preached else where. By Richard Sheldon, Doctor in Diuinitie, his Maiesties chaplaine. In the preface whereof, there is also a briefe inquirie made by him, into a late sermon, stiled, The communion of saints.</title>
            <author>Sheldon, Richard, d. 1642?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117178</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852393</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12090)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1081:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ, on his throne; not in popish secrets A prophecie of Christ, against his pretended presence in popish secrets; laid open in a sermon preached before his Maiestie at Wansted certaine yeares agoe, and since much inlarged, and (vpon request) preached else where. By Richard Sheldon, Doctor in Diuinitie, his Maiesties chaplaine. In the preface whereof, there is also a briefe inquirie made by him, into a late sermon, stiled, The communion of saints.</title>
                  <author>Sheldon, Richard, d. 1642?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Humfrey Lownes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The communion of saints" is by Edward Maie.</note>
                  <note>The title page is a cancel. Variant: with cancellandum title page, which has "else-where" and "sermon styled The".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maie, Edward. --  Sermon of the communion of saints --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17710:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17710:1"/>
            <p>CHRIST, ON HIS THRONE; <hi>NOT</hi> In POPISH Secrets.</p>
            <p>A Prophecie of Chriſt, againſt his pretended preſence in <hi>Popiſh Secrets;</hi> Laid open in a Sermon preached before his Maieſtie at WANSTED <hi>certaine yeares agoe, and ſince much</hi> inlarged, and (vpon requeſt) preached <hi>elſe-where.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By RICHARD SHELDON, <hi>Doctor in Diuinitie,</hi> his Maieſties Chaplaine.</p>
            <p>In the Preface whereof, there is alſo a briefe Inquirie made <hi>by him, into a late Sermon ſtyled</hi> The Communion of Saints.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The fleſh of Chriſt, becauſe it is in heauen, aſſuredlie it is not on Earth.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Vigil. cont. Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ic. lib. 4. cap. 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Humfrey Lowne.</hi> 1622</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17710:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17710:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull and vertuous Ladie, <hi>Philip,</hi> wife of the Right worſhipfull and <hi>Right worthie Sir</hi> Anthonie Aſhley, <hi>Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAME:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene &amp; is an euer-vſance of Authours, in publiſhing their works, to make free choiſe of ſom worthy <hi>Patron</hi> or <hi>Patroneſſe:</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards theſe, acknowledging a dutie of <hi>Gratitude;</hi> In others, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring and honouring the <hi>luſtre</hi> of thoſe vertues whereon they treate, for ſome, aduenturing to giue further inſtruction, and incouragement, in their moſt approued endeuours; from all, crauing the honour of <hi>Patronage;</hi> to all, recording (for all Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities, ſo much as may lie in them) a <hi>perpetuitie</hi> of a memorable <hi>fame.</hi> An honourable ſeruice, which (if of worth) all <hi>Worthies</hi> haue euer accepted grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and worthily.</p>
            <p>Modeſt <hi>Ladie,</hi> tis alſo a modeſt boldnes of Truth eſpecially of Chriſtian <hi>Truth,</hi> that ſhe dare knock and craue welcome at the Gates of all thoſe, who are <hi>Louers</hi> of <hi>Truth: Great is Truth and euer preuaileth, euer iuſtified of her owne Children.</hi> My ſelfe then, who com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this <hi>Dedication,</hi> with a <hi>Preſent</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> doe preſume a Welcome with her who is a Child of
<pb facs="tcp:17710:3"/> 
               <hi>Truth,</hi> a Daughter of Religious <hi>Parents (Parents</hi> of diuerſe Children louers of <hi>Truth</hi>) all Louers of Truth; of that <hi>Truth</hi> (I ſay) whereof the beloued <hi>Diſciple</hi> hath written, that it <hi>abode in the Ladie Elect, himſelfe, her Children, and was alſo to abide in them for for euer.</hi> A Welcome then, and gracious accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance I doe preſume, and aſſure to my ſelfe, in this my ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Three words onely, of three reaſons (omitting others) for this my <hi>Dedication.</hi> Firſt, in you, a cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Modeſtie</hi> (when I name <hi>Modeſtie,</hi> I name an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured <hi>Emblem</hi> of all vertues) which I haue obſerued in you, but haue more fully heard of you. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, for you, an intended confirmation of your faith in that Chriſtian <hi>Truth</hi> whereof you are a <hi>Louer,</hi> and ſincere <hi>Profeſſor.</hi> Thirdly, from my ſelfe a duetie of <hi>Gratitude</hi> towards you, acknowledging your euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readyneſſe for my good; your oft moſt louing and kind inquirie after the <hi>Welfare</hi> of thoſe who are mine, and who, in the obligation of <hi>Gratitude,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with my ſelfe are and ſhall bee yours. The God of <hi>Truth</hi> confirme you in all <hi>Truth,</hi> bleſſe and perfect your Right worthie <hi>Knight</hi> with your ſelfe, in all increaſe and aboundance of temporall and eternall happineſſe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips moſt deuoted in all Chriſtian ſeruice, <hi>RICHARD SHELDON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17710:3"/>
            <head>Certain Aduertiſements to <hi>the Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Firſt Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian and courteous Reader, I aduertiſe thee in a few things. Firſt, if thou bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reade, peruſe ſeriouſly, conſider ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely, and then judge vnpartially. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member well, that it is an obſcure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy which I heer endeauour to explane. If thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueſt any more literall and genuine, or myſticall and more likely ſenſe thereof, I pray thee to impart it without enuy; if not, at leaſt giue me leaue to communicate this vnto thee, as both a probable and approueable ſenſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till a better, more genuine and certaine, bee produced. Sure I am, that it is agreeing to the analogie of faith, and tends to the beating down of an execrable point of <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> daily practiſed in the popiſh Church.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Second Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſement.</note> Secondly, I aduertiſe thee, if thou be a <hi>Papiſt-Proteſtant,</hi> that is, more <hi>Papiſt</hi> than <hi>Proteſtant;</hi> or a <hi>Proteſtant-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist,</hi> that is, more Chriſtian than <hi>Papiſt,</hi> yet in part po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh (for, by ſuch mongrell meddleis at Maſſe and at Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, the <hi>myſtery of iniquity</hi> now worketh powerfully &amp; perfidiouſly) if thou be ſuch a one (I ſay) then this my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation will ſurely at the firſt ſeem to thee altogether incredible, and a very paradox: but if in the vnpartiall peruſing thereof, the ſame may happen to ſeem probable to thee, then bethink thy ſelf what myſteries of iniquitie are taught in <hi>Babylon;</hi> when-as a ſecond myſtery thereof being laid open, fore-told and fore-condemn'd by Chriſt, the ſame ſeems ſo prodigiouſly incredible.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Third Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement.</note> In the third place I aduertiſe thee, that wheras in page 20. I doo call that Propoſition blaſphemous, wherein the
<pb facs="tcp:17710:4"/> popiſh Prieſt is ſtiled <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Creatoris ſui, the creator of his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 20</note> 
               <hi>Creator;</hi> and doo likewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epute for impious, that (if ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken properly and literally) <hi>the Prieſt ore proprio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onficit cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> though he vſe this phraſe in his epiſtle <hi>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> yet moſt certain it is, that he vnder ſtands not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me literally, but of a myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll making of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, called Chriſts body. See him in 26. Mat <hi>&amp; ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. q.</hi> 2</note> 
               <hi>domini, with his owne mouth mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the body of the Lord;</hi> and thereupon is ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>The Maker of the Lords bodie, of Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> body</hi> I aduertiſe thee (I ſay) that thou do not think that heerin I ſpecially and principally aimed againſt the ſaid Propoſition, as it is la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y printed in a certaine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, ſtiled <hi>The Communion of Saints:</hi> and yet, it beeing there, I cannot wel paſs by it without a little enquirie.</p>
            <p>Touching which Propoſition, that hath giuen (as it is there deliuered) very great offenſe to many; I my ſelfe, finding ſuch variety in the impreſſions of the ſaid Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, for my owne ſatisfaction haue made diligent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry concerning the allowed copie, and for the ſame haue receiued moſt certain and aſſured inſtruction, thus: Firſt, that theſe words, <hi>The makers of Chriſts body,</hi> together with the other, <hi>creatores Creatoris, the creators of their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator,</hi> were indeed offered in the written Copie by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, to haue been approued, but that they were vtterly diſallowed, and the Author alſo ſtrictly required to leaue them out; as alſo diuerſe other paſſages (heerafter queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned) which were likely to giue juſt offenſe. And leſt the Reader might gather ſome like ſenſe from other words going before in page 6. touching the Prieſts <hi>power ouer</hi>
               <note place="margin">page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſts naturall body;</hi> theſe words, <hi>They make vp the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body of Chriſt by the holy Ghoſt</hi> (heerin alluding to the
<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 16</note> Apoſtles phraſe) were expreſly required by the R. Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to be added in place of the former. So carefull and wary was the learned and judicious Cenſurer of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, had not the Authour taken ſuch a wilfull liberty to himſelf, not to print what he was allowed, but in diuerſe things what he liſted or luſted.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place I am informed, when-as (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſtrict inhibition) theſe words, <hi>The makers of Chriſts body,</hi> were thruſt into the firſt printed Copie, and
<pb facs="tcp:17710:4"/> the Author challenged for it, he promiſed in the next im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion (which he then had in hand) to giue full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: but in that impreſſion, in ſtead of omitting thoſe words, he claps-on a large marginall Comment of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain annotations familiar with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> though (God wot) not prouing his intent. And heerupon, greater of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe beeing taken than before, and an ouerture made of calling in his books (in regard of ſuch indirect and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue dealing) he yeelded in the end to inſert by way of parentheſis, for further explication, theſe words (<hi>to weet, in a ſacramentall and myſticall ſenſe</hi>). But yet it is to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that he doth it not without a pretty ſleight: for, immediately after the parentheſis, hee addes, <hi>They make the myſticall bodie of Chriſt;</hi> when-as hee ſhould haue ſaid, <hi>They make vp the myſticall bodie of Chriſt;</hi> leauing out the word <hi>vp,</hi> as not agreeing to his oblique purpoſe &amp; intent</p>
            <p>Further, I vnderſtand that he being expreſly required to leaue out the word <hi>onely</hi> in the ſixt page towards the
<note place="margin">page 6</note> end therof, he did it not; but makes our Sauiour to ſpeak thoſe words (<hi>Doe this in remembrance of me</hi>) onely to his Apoſtles; perhaps thereby driuing after the popiſh ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing <hi>Facite:</hi> when-as it is moſt certain, that theſe words (<hi>Do this</hi>) haue reference to the whole myſticall action (both of Miniſter and people reſpectiuely) of <hi>bleſſing, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11</note> 
               <hi>eating, drinking, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then the Reader may obſerue, how the Author (like the fiſh called <hi>Cuttle,</hi> hiding it ſelfe with his owne
<note place="margin">Sepia ſuo ſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tramento occ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat.</note> ink) ſhuffles vp and downe, now putting-in the words (<hi>in a ſacramentall and myſticall ſenſe</hi>) now leauing them out; again, in one impreſſion putting-in the words (<hi>vp</hi> and <hi>onely</hi>) but in others leauing them out; not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (perhaps) what or whereof he affirmeth. May not the Author then (in all brotherly loue) or, if need be, his Patrone for him, if he haue any ſuch, the reuerend <hi>Nemo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nullibi</hi> (with him <hi>Conclamatiſſimus,</hi> moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamed; to others <hi>Occultatiſſimus,</hi> moſt hidde) be deſired
<pb facs="tcp:17710:5"/> to come out of his blank, and to appear in black, for the defenſe and inſtruction of his ſo vncertain and wauering a Client; that ſo wee, the poor Readers, may vnderſtand what may be the meaning and myſterie of ſuch dubious writing?</p>
            <p>With the Authors Epiſtle dedicatory, fronted in ſuch an vncouth manner, we may bee the bolder (as alſo with the Preface annexed thereunto in ſome impreſſions) for that they both haue been ſo bold as to preaſe to the Preſs without any preſenting at all to Authority for their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance to be printed.</p>
            <p>Firſt: may not the Authors diſcretion or reading bee
<note place="margin">Epiſt. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. liue 1.</note> queſtioned, for deuiſing the Epithets of <hi>Conſummatiſſimus</hi> and <hi>Conclamatiſſimus Pontificum?</hi> (thereby intending to honour his Reuerend Father in God) which Epithets are not (ſo vſed) to be found in <hi>Sidonius,</hi> as by the Author he
<note place="margin">Sid. Apol. l. 2. ep. 2. l. 7. ep. 7</note> is cited. I finde indeed in <hi>Sidonius,</hi> in his <hi>lib. 2. ep.</hi> 2. theſe words, <hi>Conclamatiſsimo fontium</hi> (the moſt famous of foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains) and in his <hi>epiſt. 7. lib.</hi> 7. in the inſcription thereof, theſe; <hi>Domino Graeco Papa, To the Lord Greek, Pope:</hi> which title <hi>Papa,</hi> Pope, though in antient times it was vſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly to Biſhops; yet, becauſe the Author impoſeth no ſpeciall name vpon his masked Patrone, may not I with others conjecture, that he intendeth for his Patron that Pope who is now onely ſo called <hi>per eminentiam,</hi> and claimeth to bee <hi>Conclamatiſsimus,</hi> moſt conclamed ouer the whole Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>What ſpirit of meeknes is in thoſe words of the ſayd
<note place="margin">Epiſt. ded. pag. 2</note> Epiſtle? <hi>Thoſe to haue neuer taſted of the ſpirit of goodnes, who</hi> (as the Authors phraſe is) <hi>did cut him for his Sermon;</hi> and likewiſe in thoſe, wherein he taxeth thoſe with <hi>intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to the Reader, page 1</note> 
               <hi>maleuolence,</hi> who had ſaid <hi>that his Sermon was called in;</hi> when as (as hee there glorieth) <hi>it was called out?</hi> But how may it iuſtly be ſaid of thoſe, that <hi>they had neuer taſted of the ſpirit of goodnes,</hi> or that they had <hi>intemperate maleuolence,</hi> for that they reprooued that Sermon which was ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently
<pb facs="tcp:17710:5"/> ſuſpected to fauour <hi>Papiſm,</hi> and alſo to be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the allowed and approoued Copie?</p>
            <p>He glorieth that his Sermon was ſo faſt called out: for my part, I maruell not thereat; conſidering how great a number of <hi>Perſonated</hi> and <hi>Parſonated</hi> (Chameleon-like) Prieſts, in all habits and ſhapes, all colours and faſhions ſaue their owne) doo daily ſpatiate in <hi>Pauls,</hi> and walk through <hi>Pauls Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yard.</hi> And will not ſuch diſguiſed <hi>Maſſers, makers of Chriſts body</hi> (perhaps hauing it in their
<note place="margin">The Sermon, page 6. 7</note> boſomes or their pockets) <hi>creators of their Creator,</hi> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre to <hi>call out</hi> ſuch a Sermon, wherein their <hi>powerfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Chriſts body (ore proprio, with the Prieſts own mouth) is ſo plainly maintained;</hi> wherein they may finde diuerſe Authors (ſome dubious, ſome counterfet) approuingly related for the maintenance of ſuch erroneus points as to them are gratefull? Heer they may reade of the barbarous and forged Epiſtle of <hi>Pope Pontian,</hi> the counterfet <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi>
               <note place="margin">page 7. 2. <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pr:</hi> page 9. 10 <hi>Epiſtele</hi> to the Reader.</note> of <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> the moſt vain and dream<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> like forged <hi>Constitutions</hi> of <hi>Clement.</hi> How gratefully will they <hi>call out,</hi> and ſolace themſelues, with that Sermon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all thoſe are roundly cenſured <hi>to goe out of the way, who to ſhew the doctrine of that Church</hi> (the Authour meaneth Rome) <hi>doo blazon the liues and doctrines of particular men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will it not ſerue them for and in ſtead of an inter-lude
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to the Reader in the Ende.</note> to <hi>call out</hi> and to reade that Sermon, wherein they may finde a Miniſter of the Church of England praying to Angels? And though hee pray in <hi>Bernards</hi> phraſe (who was carried away with the errour of the time) yet they will begin to conceiue, that the <hi>Society</hi> wherein the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> liued is not far off from the approuing of Saint-<hi>inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> yea and of <hi>tranſubſtantiation</hi> alſo (in regard of what he writeth in his Sermon, page 7.) with ſuch other <hi>Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhips</hi> as doo ineuitably flowe and follow thence-from. Which their conception is but a mere deception; like to that their pernicious Lie (now vauntingly in print) that the late moſt entire and religious Biſhop of <hi>London, Iohn</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17710:6"/> Doctor <hi>King</hi> died a Papiſt, a reconciled Papiſt. O the impudent and ſhameleſſe fore-head of ſuch men! <hi>Poſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ſpem ſuam mendacium, they haue made lying to bee their</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 28. 1. 1. Tim. 3. 13.</note> 
               <hi>hope. So they haue euer done, ſo they yet doo, &amp; proficient in peins,</hi> and heerin they will (if I aim not amiſſe) do worſe: for, Papiſm is well-nigh arriued <hi>ad</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to the height of her deception.</p>
            <p>Further, though it ſhould coſt them dear, yet they will <hi>call out,</hi> and pry into that Sermon, in the <hi>Preface</hi> whereof
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> To the Reader.</note> they may finde <hi>a world of warriours</hi> (ſuch warriors as haue written againſt the <hi>Tridentine Synod</hi>) to be branded with the <hi>choice and election of the pleaſure of temporall ſin.</hi> What?
<note place="margin">pag. 3. Heb. 11. 25.</note> all ſuch warriours that haue oppoſed the Lady <hi>Hellen</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> (whether <hi>Royall, Clerks,</hi> or <hi>Laickes</hi>)? what? all (I ſay) <hi>Louers of pleaſures, more than of God?</hi> and yet all <hi>Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11 26.</note> and <hi>Interimiſts</hi> (Author-like) <hi>aſpicientes in remunera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem,</hi> aiming at that reward which God hath promiſed to thoſe that loue him? O egregious! ſuch onely louers of God, who endeauour to join <hi>light</hi> and <hi>darknes, Christ</hi> and <hi>Belial, God</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> that is, two moſt oppoſite reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions? It will not bee vnacceptable to them, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in his Epiſtle dedicatorie, page 3, inueigheth ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly againſt Sermon-haunters: wherin perhaps he wold ſhrowd himſelf, by pretended oppoſing the oppoſers of Church-gouernment. But may he not look further, and thereby obliquely ſtrike at our Church? A practice not vnuſuall heertofore (to my knowledge) in ſome indirect ſquinters againſt the doctrine and diſcipline of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Author, in the ſame place, much complaineth of a <hi>corrupted liuer</hi> (Oh how ſick, and deadly ſick, would hee
<note place="margin">Epiſt. ded. pag. 4</note> make this famous Church to be!) <hi>of a corrupted liuer, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to cauſe the ſound doctrine of our Redeemer to proue loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and none but ſcrubbers to be in requeſt. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ah! the ſound doctrine of our Redeemer proue loathſome! Out alack! none but ſcrubbers in requeſt!</hi> The Church of Rome (I knowe what I write) would buy it dearly, that there were fewer of ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:17710:6"/> 
               <hi>ſcrubbers,</hi> who haue ſcrubbed vp ſo vnceſſantly &amp; ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the roots of her errours, that the very bloud of her ſhame is thereby diſcouered, and by them laid open to the view both of men and Angels: And heerin I meane ſuch handlers of controuerſies, preachers and lecturers, as are approoued in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and allowed by Authority; and, to my vnderſtanding, the Author le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, againſt ſuch, his bitter and tart nick-name <hi>ſcrubbers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe phraſes of the Authour (which hee was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ser.</hi> pages 1. 10 11. and 4. 5.</note> to amend) in his Sermon, page 1, <hi>The three Saints;</hi> page 10, <hi>The three firſt Saints;</hi> page 11, <hi>Some are Saints by ſubstantiall ſanctitie, &amp;c.</hi> and in page 4. and 5. <hi>The ſecond Saint:</hi> Are not theſe phraſes very harſh (if not dangerous) in ſo ſacred a myſterie? Let them be compared with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> his <hi>Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not to be omitted, that thoſe words (<hi>ſetting aſide the efficacie of inſpired Scripture</hi>) which were required with ſome other to be put in the allowed Copie (and for which the Author is beholding to his learned Cenſurer) were wilfully left out in the firſt Impreſſion. And though they be put-in into the ſecond Impreſſion, yet doo they alone hardly make good that Saying, <hi>The preaching of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks can conuert no more, than a good morall ſentence out of</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca. Surely, if ſuch preaching or teaching as may bee
<note place="margin">His moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties religious Meditations: His diuine and exquiſite <hi>Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ron:</hi> his other Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall workes. Acts 8. 25. 26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. 28. Acts 8. 5.</note> vſed by <hi>Kings</hi> to their Subiects, <hi>Generals</hi> to their Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Maſters</hi> to their Families, by Scholars for exerciſe, or ſuch as Chriſtian Authors may deliuer in print (for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the Lord <hi>Pleſſie Mornay,</hi> and others at home) bee not able <hi>to conuert more, than a good morall ſentence out of</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca; yet I hope the Author will not dare to denie, but that the teaching or preaching of <hi>Priſcilla</hi> and <hi>Aquila,</hi> of <hi>Apollo,</hi> of the
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en. l. b.</hi> 3. c. 12. <hi>Doroth.</hi> in <hi>Synop.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eunuch</hi> of the Queen <hi>Candaces,</hi> and of the Chriſtians diſperſed from Hieruſalem, did conuert more, than anie the beſt morall ſentence out of <hi>Seneca</hi> could haue done. Hath the Author read in <hi>Seneca</hi> ought concerning Chriſt, and ſaluation by him? who
<pb facs="tcp:17710:7"/> thus (debaſing) compareth the teaching of Chriſtian do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (though by Laicks) to morall ſentences fetcht out of <hi>Seneca.</hi> Yet far be it from mee to allow any other tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching by Laicks, then according as I haue heer expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Should I haue written ſuch a Sermon, and haue alike intituled it <hi>The Communion of Saints,</hi> I ſhould not haue da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to taxe all the <hi>Hoſte</hi> of the Lord (from the daies of our Sauior) for their neglect of duty in ſuch a ſeruice. Let vs ponder his words, <hi>By how much the communion of</hi>
               <note place="margin">page 21.</note> 
               <hi>Saints hath been neglected: for, from the daies of our Sauiour, vntill this houre</hi> (he reckons to the very time of the clocks ſtroke for his Sermon) <hi>not one man hath been ſo charitable to the Saints, as to beſtowe one whole Sermon vpon their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion (for any thing that I can finde) nor any iust Treatiſe (one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome little expoſitions) except onely one Schiſmatick, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriates that Communion moſt vniuſtly to his own ſeparation.</hi> Thus the Author. Hath he not forgotten (or elſe he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands them not) Saint <hi>Auſtines</hi> Book <hi>de vnitate Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae?</hi> his exquiſite Volume <hi>de ciuitate Dei? Cyprian de vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Eccleſiae,</hi> or <hi>de ſimplicitate Praelatorum? Gerſon de vnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te eccleſiastica?</hi> How many Authors, in their ſhort expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions vpon the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> and in their Comments vpon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and vpon the 17. of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> haue deliuered a great deal more ſubſtance (touching this Communion of Saints) in a few words, than the Author hath don in this his ſo vne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en and vnconſonant a Sermon? Could the Authour neither ſee nor ſmell, in that ſweet field of Doctor <hi>Field, of the Church,</hi> many fragrant paſſages touching this Argument? Maruell, he could not obſerue <hi>Bellarmine</hi> treating (after his faſhion)
<note place="margin">Bellar. tom. 2.</note> on the Communion of the <hi>Saints militant, patient</hi> and <hi>triumphant.</hi> I my ſelf, within theſe few years, haue heard (in this Church of England) from the mouthes of ſuch
<note place="margin">D. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. M. D.</note> (as the Author would perhaps haue reputed <hi>ſcrubbers</hi>) very exquiſite Sermons on this Subiect. And haue not the like been done in all times when and where the goſpell of Chriſt hath flouriſhed?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17710:7"/>
            <p>To conclude, (pretermitting manie other points in his epiſtles, worthie either of redargution, or requiring interpretation) I doe finally note, how in his epiſtle to
<note place="margin">Pag. 2. line 26</note> the Reader, hee promiſeth thus; <hi>wee ſhall ſearch, how farre that doctrine</hi> (hee meaneth the <hi>Trid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntine) will admit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union?</hi> What? <hi>reunion?</hi> And may not the Authour here be aduiſed, to thinke of his owne ſtrength; whether this bee feiſible by him or no: let him conſider, whether hee hath iudgement ſufficient to reſolue, diſcretion to order, ability to bring forth ſuch a Childe; hee (I ſay) who (though hee hath taken libertie, to haue printed (in diuers things) what hee hath liſted) hath notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (after manie trauailes) brought forth with a double birth ſo imperfect an <hi>Embryo;</hi> according as, in part, it hath beene ſhewed, and more might bee added.</p>
            <p>More Doubts and demaundes I might haue propoſed; but theſe maie ſuffice: the which I deſire both the Authour and all courteous Readers to take no otherwiſe then as ſo many requeſts that the Authour would bee pleaſed to open and explane himſelfe more fully.</p>
            <p>But, for ſo much as may concerne his pretended <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamatiſsimus,</hi> moſt <hi>Conclamed Patrone,</hi> Lette him not take it amiſſe, if I preſume, and conclude that there muſt bee a latent myſtery, and emblem of ſome forraine obiect intended in this riddling dedication. For ſure among the Reuerend <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous for learning, ſo ſolid and ſound for iudgement (whoſe worthie names aduance our Church aboue other Reformed) there will none be found to fauour theſe dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, looſe and ill ſounding poſitions, which I haue here in part freely &amp; ingenuouſly noted; and this for no other ende, then to craue the Authours Brotherly explanation: the which I heartily wiſh hee may performe to his owne content and to the Chriſtian ſatisfaction of others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> My fourth Aduertiſement is, that whereas the courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader cannot but obſerue my following diſcourſe
<pb facs="tcp:17710:8"/> to bee ſome what tart and pregnant againſt the errours of Poperie; my aduertiſement to him is, that hee would bee pleaſed to interpret the ſame not as proceeding out of any ſpleene againſt their perſons, but onelie out of an vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned zeale againſt their errours and vanities. God is my witneſſe, that in the bowels of Charitie I could wiſh to my ſelfe, for their ſaluation, Saint Paules <hi>Anatheme,</hi> which hee <hi>deſired to himſelfe, for his brethren according to the fleſh:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Rom. 9. 1. 2.</note> And yet I cannot but remember (for I haue obſerued it well) that their Spirit towardes ſuch as my ſelfe, hath been and is a verie <hi>gall of bitterneſſe;</hi> furie rather then zeal. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<note place="margin">Iude. Mat. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Iude</hi> hath deſcribed their Spirits: and our Sauiour hath charged vs to beware of them.</p>
            <p>For ſo much as ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e concerne my zeale againſt their dotages and ſuperſticions, I hope the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> example af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his <hi>conuerſion from Iudaiſme</hi> confronting and <hi>Confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> the <hi>Iewes,</hi> may aboundantly be ſufficient for me. And is not this my zeale an expreſſe imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (without enuie be it ſpoken) of the zeale of all thoſe holie &amp; bleſſed <hi>Seruants</hi> and <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of God which his <hi>Spirit</hi> hath raiſed vp (from out of the very <hi>Vr</hi> of popery, &amp; fornance of <hi>Babylon</hi>) for the oppoſing him and his whom <hi>the Lord Ieſus ſhall deſtroy illuſtratione aduentus gloriae ſuae, with the brightnes of his comming,</hi> the Glory of his Goſpell? The phraſes which I produce (<hi>Antichriſt, falſe prophets, falſe-anointed-ones, idelatry, blaſphemous,</hi> with ſuch like) will not ſeeme harſh, nor ill-ſounding to the Intelligent Reader, who may bee inſtructed in the Scriptures of God, and who alſo may be
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luther. Cal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et. Mart. Beza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lan.</hi> Others.</note> pleaſed to call to mynde, what tart phraſes the right fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Conuerts from Poperie haue vſed againſt <hi>Babylon;</hi> and (to adde no more) who laſtly will haue in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the many zealous actions, ſpeeches, and writings which Primitiue Chriſtians vſed againſt <hi>Idolatrous Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſme,</hi> after their happy conuerſion from the ſame.</p>
            <p>And ſo moſt humbly referring all my poore ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, to the honour of him who is the one Onely God,
<pb facs="tcp:17710:8"/> moſt <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>moſt wiſe;</hi> I remit my ſelfe, and this my w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iting, freely to the ordinary Readers cenſure, <hi>pro libito;</hi> but in all due reſpect, and humble reuerence, to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Superious, and of Chriſts holy Church <hi>Catholicke, pro venerabils placito, for her venerable Placet</hi> and gracious approueance.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated <date>this 1. of <hi>February.</hi> 1622.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus, RICHARD SHELDON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17710:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17710:9"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>If therefore they ſhall ſay vnto you, Behould, he is in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, beleeue it not</p>
                  <bibl>Mat. 24. 26.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the contagion of originall ſinne, all <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity is ſo darkned and depraued, <hi>ſpolia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta gratuitis, vulnerata in naturalibus,</hi> ſpoyled of the free gifts of grace, and wounded in all the faculties of nature; that the very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, among a maſſe of other errors, doo there ſhew themſelues hardy-confident, where they ſhould bee pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly-timorous; there, <hi>trepidantes ſine timore,</hi> trembling without any juſt cauſe of fear, where they ſhould bee ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly-vigilant and prouident. For example: ſome pious perſons, reading the 24 of S. <hi>Mathews</hi> goſpell, in which the Euangeliſt, from the mouth of our Sauiour, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundeth ſignes in the Sunne and Moon; ſhaking and rentings of the heauens; fallings of ſtars from the ſame; warres, and rumours of wars; vnſeaſonable inequalities of the air; famines, plagues, peſtilences, earth-quakes, with ſundry ſuch like, which were to happen before the finall conſummation of the world; reading theſe things (I ſay) they are with aſtoniſhment well-nie confounded: whereas (becauſe they are but as ſo many fore-warnings of the Lords coming, and their redemption) they ſhould be ſoberly and joyfully vigilant: And yet theſe very men peruſing ſome other paſſages of this 24 chapter, where they are fore-warned of farre more dangerous things, to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17710:10"/> wit, of the ariſing of ſundry falſe prophets, of falſe Chriſts (in diuers ſtates and times of the Church) who were to teach a corporall and ſecret preſence of Chriſt in Secrets;
<note place="margin">How neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this prophecie is.</note> and, for proof of the ſame alſo, were to doo great ſignes and wonders, euen to the ſeducing of the Elect if it were poſſible; heer they are hardy-confident, as though this fore charge of Chriſt little or nothing at all concerned them. And yet our moſt gracious Sauiour (who is <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uandorum omnium via, veritas &amp; vita,</hi> the way, life &amp; truth of all thoſe who are to bee ſaued: the way, to conduct them; the truth, to inſtruct them; the life, to ſaue them from periſhing) that hee might deeply imprint in the mindes of his faithfull a true apprehenſion of ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which might ariſe from ſuch falſe Prophets, he is not contented once or twice to haue commanded vigilancie againſt them, but he doth oft recommend warineſſe and watchfulneſſe againſt them, and their ſo powerfully-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious doctrines.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe, hauing in the 23. 24. and 25. verſes of
<note place="margin">Math. 24. 23. 24. 25.</note> this chapter (though in a generality) foretold the ariſing of ſome falſe prophets, in the 23. thus; <hi>Then if any one ſhall ſay vnto you, Loe, heer is Chriſt, lo, there is Chriſt, beleeue it not;</hi> in the 24. verſe, <hi>For, there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes and wonders; inſomuch that, if it were poſſible, they ſhall deceiue the very Elect;</hi> In the 25. verſe he thundreth out thus, <hi>Behould, I haue fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tould you: behould, I haue tould you before.</hi> And yet, not content heerwith, he doth in the verſes following more particularly expreſſe the manner of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their falſe-teaching of his preſence vpon earth, in Secrets; and alſo redoubles
<note place="margin">chriſts charge.</note> this charge againſt them in the 26. thus: <hi>If they ſhall ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, Behold, he is in the deſert, go not out; behould, he is in the Secrets, beleeue it not.</hi> And then, for further confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſo ſtraight a forewarning, he adjoynes in the
<note place="margin">A double rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his charge.</note> 27. and 28. verſes a twofould reaſon for the ſame: The former in the 27, thus; <hi>For, as the lightning commeth from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17710:10"/> the Eaſt, and ſhineth euen vnto the West: ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of man be:</hi> The ſecond reaſon in the 28. verſe, thus; <hi>For, whereſoeuer the dead body is, there ſhall the Eagles be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together.</hi> This, our moſt tender and gracious Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, for the neceſſary fore-inſtruction of his faithfull.</p>
            <p>To meditate on this whole argument fully, an houres moment will not permit. In which reſpect, I will limit my diſcourſe to thoſe words (part of the 26. verſe) which I haue read in your religious eares. <hi>If therefore they ſhall ſay vnto you, Behould, he is in the Penetrals or Secrets, beleeue it not.</hi> This my Text is mixt; containing a prediction, a
<note place="margin">The diuiſion of the text.</note> falſe doctrine or <hi>pſeudo-christianiſme,</hi> a charge and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The prophecie and prediction is Chriſts: the falſe doctrine and <hi>pſeudo-chriſtianiſme</hi> is of the <hi>pſeudo</hi>-Chriſts and falſe Prophets. The precept and direction is againe Chriſts. The firſt requires faith and beleef; the ſecond, diſ-beleef and contempt; the third, duty and obedience. The prediction we haue in thoſe words, <hi>If therefore they ſhall ſay vnto you;</hi> the <hi>pſeudo-christianiſme</hi> in theſe, <hi>Behould, he is in the Penetrals or Secrets;</hi> the charge and direction in the reſt, <hi>beleeue it not.</hi> Of theſe in order, as God (who once ſpake them) ſhall be pleaſed to aſſiſt with his grace.</p>
            <p>Touching the firſt, the prediction, I will only ſuppoſe foure things genuinely and naturally flowing from the
<note place="margin">Fower breefe ſuppoſitions. The firſt.</note> ſame. Firſt, that howſoever this prophecie bee deliuered conditionally with this conjunction <hi>if, If they ſhall ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you;</hi> yet that the ſame is abſolute, ſure and certain, equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualent with this, When they ſhall ſay vnto you, or, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<note place="margin">Chriſts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction though conditionally deliuered yet abſolutely cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</note> they ſhall and will ſay vnto you. So that the word <hi>If</hi> is not vſed heer in reſpect of the contingencie of the thing, but rather in regard of the vncertainty of the time when: for, that ſuch falſe Prophets (who would ſo teach) were infallibly to ariſe, it is moſt euident by thoſe words of Chriſt, in the 24. verſe: <hi>For, there ſhall ariſe many falſe Prophets, and falſe Chriſts</hi> (that is, falſe anointed ones) <hi>and ſhall doe great ſignes and wonders, euen to the ſeducing of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17710:11"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Suppoſition </seg>2</label> Elect, if it were poſſible.</hi> The ſecond thing which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is, that by the Pronoun (<hi>they</hi>) is deſigned a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and great troop of falſe teachers and falſe anointed ones, who all ſhould iointly, and at ſundry times<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in ſundry places, teach Chriſt to <hi>be heer and there,</hi> in ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret manner of preſence vpon earth. So that we may not heer think of one <hi>Hacket,</hi> one <hi>Copinger,</hi> as in <hi>England</hi> (therein moſt vnfortunate) nor of one <hi>George Dauid,</hi> as in <hi>Germany;</hi> but wee muſt think of an immenſe troop, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of an <hi>exercitus ſacerdotum</hi> (to vſe <hi>Gregories</hi> phraſe) <hi>a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. l. 4. ep. 33</note> 
               <hi>whole army of falſe Prophets and falſe Chriſts</hi> (that is, falſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed ones) who were (to the deception of innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) to teach a reall, ſecret preſence of Chriſt in <hi>Penetrals</hi> vpon earth, before his coming to judgement.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Suppoſition </seg>3</label> Thirdly, I ſuppoſe, that by the word <hi>ſay, ſay vnto you;</hi> are compriſed all manners of their deliuering this their <hi>pſeudo-chriſtianiſme,</hi> whether it bee by pen in print, or by tongue in pulpit, and priuate conference; commending, and by miracles endeauouring to perſwade and eſtabliſh this their <hi>Pſeudo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> christianiſme</hi> of Chriſts being in Secrets, therein to be beheld, adored and worſhipped.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Suppoſition </seg>4</label> My fourth ſuppoſition is, that by the Pronoune <hi>you, when they ſhall ſay vnto you,</hi> are vnderſtood all thoſe whom theſe falſe Prophets ſhall endeauour to peruert &amp; ſeduce: and who elſe can theſe be but the faithfull? who beeing, according to the faith of the Primitiue Church, taught to look for none, nor to think of any corporall preſence of Chriſt vpon earth, <hi>in ſecrets and in holes;</hi> Yet theſe falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>turpis quaeſtus cauſâ,</hi> for filthy lucres ſake, and to purchaſe to themſelues names to be <hi>creatores Creatoris ſui,</hi> creators of their Creator, ſhall endeauour moſt powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſeduce them by this errour: wherein they ſhall ſo far preuail, that the <hi>Elect</hi> ſhall be in hazard to be peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;
<note place="margin">The Elect in danger to bee peruerted, a point of high unportance.</note> a circumſtance of ſuch importance (<hi>that the Elect ſhall be in danger to be ſeduced</hi>) that it doth more than moſt manifeſtly euince to mee, that the ſignes which they ſhall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17710:11"/> doe, ſhall be both many and verie great: and againe; that they ſhall not deny the true Chriſt; nor pretend to teach another Chriſt (for in ſuch a Caſe in what danger of ſeduction would or could the Elect bee?) but out of Chriſts Prophecie, doctrine, and in his name, they ſhould endeuour, to teach a preſence of the true Chriſt himſelfe in <hi>ſecret</hi> &amp; in <hi>Penetralls.</hi> And ſo theſe fower things which be ſo cleare, I only ſuppoſe, not adding any further proofs of the ſame; for hee who is ouerdiligent in the proofe of cleare things, ſheweth that hee hath more time then mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, more leaſure then Iudgement. Onely I aduiſe the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue hearers, to beare theſe things well away, <hi>alta repoſit a mente, layd vp deepely in their conſiderations:</hi> for therby they ſhall be better able to attaine vnto the vnderſtanding of our diſcourſe following; which as it is of great dificul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſo it is of great conſequence, and importance.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Behould hee is in the Secrets.</head>
               <p>Concerning this our ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part; I obſerue two points: the doctrine it ſelfe; <hi>hee is in Secrets, Chriſt is in Penetralls;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The doctrine it ſelfe of theſe falſe prophets &amp; their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</note> and the manner wherewith it is deliuered, with a <hi>Behold, behold hee is in the ſecrets, in the Penetralls.</hi> A word onely of the manner. This word <hi>behould,</hi> as it is euer demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, ſpecializing ſome ſingular thing conſiderable, or worthy to bee beheld: ſo in this place, it doth ſpecifie and ſpecialize a ſingular pretended preſence of <hi>Chriſt in ſecrets, in Penetralls,</hi> admirable, wonderfull, myſterious; ſuch as requires faith and beleefe as of a prodigious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall preſence of Chriſt. And in this reſpect it is, that Chriſt giues his expreſſe Charge, againſt that verie thing with the falſe Prophets doe require; to wit, <hi>not to beleeue (beleeue it not)</hi> that which they with ſhewing of prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies and wonders require to bee beleeued as a thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious and wonderfull. They ſay, behould hee is ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and perſonally in <hi>the ſecrets;</hi> beleeue it. Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth, and ſaith beleeue it not; for hee is not in the ſecrets. They ſay; <hi>Quod non capis, quod non vides, animoſe fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17710:12"/> fides, &amp;c. Chriſtus totus ſub vtra<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſpecie. That which</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sequent. in feſto corp. Chriſt. miſſal. Roman.</note> 
                  <hi>thou conceiueſt not, that which thou ſeeſt not, A ſtrong faith will confirme, and make ſure to thee: whole Chriſt is and remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnder and in</hi> (the ſecrets of) <hi>both kinds:</hi> but Chriſt ſaith <hi>beleeue it not, beleeue it not;</hi> they profeſſe that that is an admirable and a moſt wonderfull preſence which they commend; but Chriſt on the contrarie rechargeth that it is vaine, pſeudo-chriſtian and phantaſticall: <hi>If therefore;</hi> or thus, when therefore <hi>they ſhall ſay vnto you,</hi> Chriſt <hi>is in the ſecrets, beleeue it not,</hi> regard it not: not for that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that faith is required, that wee may beleeue that true reall and Sacramentall preſence with Chriſt hath in the true Sacrament; but for that I conſtantly affirme, that Chriſt forbiddeth the beleefe of any ſuch perſonall and carnall preſence of himſelfe in the Sacrament, ſuch as
<note place="margin">The falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (behold) inuites to faith of a prodigious corporall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</note> theſe falſe Prophets were to teach. Thus haue I ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhewed (or rather I doe ſuppoſe) that the inuitation of the falſe prophets in the word <hi>behould,</hi> is an inuitation to faith and beleefe of ſome prodigious preſence, <hi>behould he is in the Penetralls, and Secrets:</hi> that is, beleeue hee is in the Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tralls and Secrets. A myſticall hidden ſecret inuiſible and myſterious preſence of Chriſt in Secrets is then that, which theſe falſe Prophets were to teach, noted and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in this word <hi>Behould.</hi> And ſo wee come to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcuſſion of the falſe doctrine it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>He is in Secrets.</head>
               <p>And firſt; what wee are here to vnderſtand, by theſe
<note place="margin">The falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine it ſelfe.</note> 
                  <hi>Secrets,</hi> wherein Chriſt is affirmed to bee; and Secondly that theſe falſe prophets were to teach the verie true <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe (not <hi>Antichriſt</hi> nor any other pretended <hi>Chriſt</hi>) to bee in theſe <hi>Secrets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt as it is a poynt of high conſequence; ſo it is of
<note place="margin">What is to be vnderſtood by the word Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets. pſalme 8</note> great difficulty. Hee, who was once pleaſed to open the <hi>tongues of babes and infants, and from their mouthes to perfect his owne praiſe,</hi> bee pleaſed ſo to preuent, aſſiſt and follow me with his grace, that I may ſpeake truely &amp; religiouſly,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17710:12"/> and you may hear accordingly. Though it may ſeem to ſome a nouelty, yet it is moſt agreeing to the analogie of faith, as I ſhall make it appear vnto you. It is not ſuch a nouelty, but that <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> &amp; <hi>Pleſſis Mornay</hi> (though
<note place="margin">Mart. loci claſſ. 4. loc. 10. Pleſſis de Sacra. l. 4. c. 9</note> they haue but a few lines heerof) haue profeſſedly thus declared this Text; yea, and ſome of the antient Fathers ſeem much inclining heerunto, as heerafter ſhall be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Be therefore moſt attentiue, and ponder well the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration which by GOD's aſſiſtance I ſhall make: for, though <hi>(noua c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>da) my interpretation may ſeem to ſome to be new,</hi> yet it is not <hi>vt noua, ſet vt vetuſtiſſima aſtruam, that I</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Irenae. l. 4. c. 32: Orig. hom. 15. in Mat. Aug. trac. 59. in Ioan. Euſ. in vit. Conſt. l. 4. c. 45</note> 
                  <hi>endeauour</hi> thereby <hi>to bring-in any new point of faith,</hi> but to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh that which is moſt venerable, antient, and truely Apoſtolicall.</p>
               <p>And for my more vn-reproueable manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding heerin, I lay for a foundation inuiolable this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or prime aſſured Rule, receiued by all <hi>Antiquity,</hi> not reiected by any iudicious either <hi>Pontifician</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant,</hi> and for truth as clear as the heauens: to wit, that the ſacred Scriptures are euer literally, according to their
<note place="margin">An infallible rule for ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> plain ſenſe, to bee vnderſtood and interpreted, <hi>idem vt ſit ſenſus mentis, qui eſt ſonus auris; that the ſenſe of the minde be the ſame with the ſound of the eare,</hi> when-as the literall and plaine ſenſe of the ſame is neither againſt faith nor good manners, nor ſeemeth to affirm any abſurdity or impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. Now, to interpret and expound theſe words (we haue in hand) according to their plaine and literall ſenſe, maketh nothing againſt the truth of Chriſtian faith; but openeth a point of Antichriſtian <hi>pſeudo-chriſtianiſme,</hi> ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at heer by our Sauiour; neither maketh it againſt good manners, neither containeth it any impoſſibilitie: for, it declareth that which is in the daily vſe and practice of the <hi>Antichriſtian Church;</hi> and which alſo they hould
<note place="margin">That Chriſt is in the Secrets, is the corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh worſhip.</note> not onely to be poſſible, but further make it a ſecondary <hi>Corner-ſtone</hi> of all their irreligious religion. To this are directed, and for this are intended, the whole maſſe and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17710:13"/> troop of their ſuperſtitious ceremonies, and leſſer orders; and vpon this, as vpon a God amongſt men (<hi>not ſurſum, but deorſum babentes corda, having their hearts not lift vp, but caſt downe</hi>) they doo reſt the very hope of their ſaluation. In this reſpect, happy, yea thrice happy, is that man, who can dy with this God in his mouth, with this Chriſt in or vpon his ſtomack; hauing ſuch a <hi>viaticum</hi> within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Moſt of the antient Interpreters of Saint <hi>Mathewes</hi> Goſpell, ſuch as liued in the purer times of the <hi>Church,</hi> whil'ſt this Prophecy of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was not fully compleated (for, before tranſubſtantiation was fully decreed, this
<note place="margin">Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. general. Lat. ſub Innoc. 3 anno 1215</note> 
                  <hi>Pſeudo-chriſtianiſme</hi> of <hi>Chriſts being in Secrets &amp; Penetrals,</hi> to be beheld and adored, was not generally taught nor beleeued) moſt, I ſay, of the antient <hi>Interpreters</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this Text myſtically of the priuate Conuenticles &amp;
<note place="margin">Origen, auſten, apud Aqum. in Cate. in Mat. 24</note> Aſſemblies of <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> challenging to themſelues the ſpirituall preſence of Chriſt. Which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition alſo (<hi>propter conſcientiam reatus, in regard of the guiltineſſe of their conſciences</hi>) is very pleaſing to the <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rhem. Teſt. an. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. in Mat. 24</note> and all our <hi>Romaniſts:</hi> but (with reuerence be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) this expoſition is a miſtaking, and is conuinced to be ſuch, by an inſtance or two, which (pretermitting all others) I will deliuer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>Firſt</label> Firſt, if our Sauiour had meant this his prediction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt falſe Prophets, teaching a hidden preſence of him <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> and <hi>there</hi> in Deſerts, in Secrets, and in Cloſets (to vſe the Rhemiſts word) to be onely vnderſtood of the priuat
<note place="margin">Their Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Mat. 24 This doctrine of theſe falſe prophets is not to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of a pretended ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual preſence</note> Conuenticles of <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> challenging his true Church and ſpirituall preſence (by teaching of his truth) to bee onely with them, and amongſt them; then ſhould not our Sauiour haue ſpecified and deliuered any proper condition, and certaine property of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Antichriſtian Synagogue, which was not to bee confined within any one Nation; but to bee ſpread ouer all Nations and Kingdomes where Chriſts Goſpell had
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Theſ. 2</note> been taught. And yet that our Sauiour doth in this place
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17710:13"/> ſpecifie a ſpeciall and proper note, a ſure and certain mark of the ſaid vniuerſall <hi>Antichriſtian Synagogue,</hi> ſome of the antient Fathers haue expreſly taught, and the Pontificians
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſ. in hom. Orig. Hier. Hill.</hi> moſt expreſly <hi>in cate. apud A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin. &amp; can. 25. in Mat.</hi>
                  </note> themſelues doo generally confeſſe; yea, and the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Text, in the verſes precedent and ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, do more than manifeſtly euince: which alſo ſhall heerafter be more clearly proued.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance </seg>2</label> A ſecond Inſtance I adioin. If Chriſts Prophecy were myſtically to be interpreted of a ſpiritual preſence of him, in regard of his truth taught in hidden places, in the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, ſecrets, cloſets, chambers,</hi> and ſuch like; then it would ſeem, in the greateſt ruffe of the Heathniſh Romane ten perſecutions, to haue touched the Roman Church it ſelf,
<note place="margin">An inuincible reaſon.</note> when ſhee was pure and ſound in faith, and whil'ſt ſhee made the <hi>Cripts</hi> and <hi>vaults</hi> within the City, the Mount <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ract</hi> without, the deſerts and fields abroad, to bee the places of her reſidence, and her chiefeſt <hi>Sanctuaries</hi> and <hi>Aſyles</hi> againſt the furies of thoſe times. And, in good ſooth, I demand of the Pontificians themſelues, whether ſuch an interpretation will not ſeem moſt to concern the
<note place="margin">Apocal. 12. 6. 14 Viega in apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. com. in c. 12 ſect. 15.</note> true Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the times of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Raign: which, as they themſelues all teach, ſhall bee moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, publike and vniuerſall; when-as the true Church of <hi>Christ</hi> then (deſigned by the woman fleeing into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert) ſhall be diſtreſſed and obſcure, deſpiſed, and diſperſed heer and there vp and downe; preaching <hi>Chriſt</hi> heer and there, in Secrets and in Corners.</p>
               <p>I ſaid aboue, that moſt of the antient <hi>Interpreters</hi> ſeem
<note place="margin">Hill. 25. can. in Mat.</note> to interpret this prophecy of Chriſt myſtically: but ſo did not that <hi>Malleus Arrianorum, that hammer of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> S. Hillary, whoſe words I finde to bee theſe; <hi>Et ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, quia in magna vexatione poſiti erunt homines, pſeudopro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Chriſt being ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and the popiſh pſeudo-chriſtianiſm ſo vnimagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it is not to be maruelled, if the Antients attained not the ſame fully. <hi>Chryſo. hom. in Mat. 24. &amp; in ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n. Aquin. Hill. in Mat. can. 25</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>tanquam praeſentem in Chriſto opem ſint indicaturi, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis in locis Chriſtum eſſe at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> haberi mentientur; vt in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſti famulatum depreſſos vexatoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> deducant: &amp; ideo ſubdit, Surge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t enim pſeudochriſti &amp; pſeudoprophetae, &amp;c. And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17710:14"/> ſaith he, <hi>becauſe men ſhall then be in great vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, the falſe Prophets ſhall make ſhew of a preſent hope to be had in Chriſt; and ſhall lie and ſay, Chriſt is to be had in many places; that ſo they may bring into the ſeruice of Antichriſt thoſe that are ſo afflicted and vexed: and therefore it is added, For, there ſhall ariſe falſe Christs and falſe Prophets, &amp;c: thus he.</hi> Which pſeudo-Chriſts, falſe Prophets and falſe Chriſts, <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> cals <hi>miniſtros Antichriſti, the ſeruants and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Antichriſt. Hillarie</hi> again addes: <hi>Nam pſeudopro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae, de quibus ſupra dixerat, nunc in deſerto Chriſtum eſſe dicent, vt homines errore deprauent; nunc in penetralibus aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent eum eſſe, vt homines dominantis Antichriſti poteſtate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludant: ſed Dominus ſe nec loco occultandum, nec à ſingulis ſeorſim contuendum proſitetur, ſed vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, &amp; in conſpectu omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um praeſentem ſe futurum eſſe denun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iat. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndeſequitur, Sicut enim fulgur, &amp;c. For the falſe Prophets of whom hee had ſaid before they ſhall ſay Chriſt to bee in the deſert, that thereby they may depraue by errour; now they will ſay him to be in Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets and Penetrals, that they may bring men into the ſubiection of Antichriſt, raigning and triumphing euerie where: but our Lord profeſſeth, that he wil neither be to be hidden in anie place, nor to be ſeen a-part by anie; but he denounceth, that he will be euerie where, and in the ſight of all. And therefore it followeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 27</note> 
                  <hi>For, as the lightning, &amp;c.</hi> Thus <hi>Hillarie.</hi> I adde a ſaying of
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Mat.</hi> 24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 6</note> 
                  <hi>Hierome: In quo oſtendit, quòd ſecundus aduent us non in humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate vt primus, ſed in gloria demonſtrandus eſt: ſtultameſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eum in paruo loco quaerere, vel in abſcondito, qui totius mundi lumen eſt. Wherein he ſheweth, that his ſecond comming ſhall not be in humilitie as the firſt, but in glorie</hi> (and doth not this make againſt his baſe being in Secrets, in boxes, in a rats belly, &amp;c?) <hi>It is therfore a fooliſh thing to ſeek him either in a little place, or in the ſecret, who is the light of the world.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note theſe words <hi>in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle place. Chryſ. hom. in 24. Mat. Euſ. apud Aqum.</hi>
                  </note> Thus <hi>Hierome;</hi> in part attaining to the knowledge of the popiſh <hi>pſeudo-christianiſme</hi> heerin. So <hi>Hillarie</hi> likewiſe, and Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> aboue; and not vnlikely <hi>Euſebius</hi> cited by <hi>Aquinas,</hi> in his <hi>Catena</hi> vpon the 17. of S. <hi>Luke.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17710:14"/>
               <p>Here by the waie, with your Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patience, I may not omit to obſerue what <hi>Maldonat's</hi> (a moſt famous Ieſuit or Ignatian) interpretation is on this place. His father-hood, who in other places is verie large, yet giueth this text a very ſhort Cut, thus: <hi>Poſuit duo, pro omnibus, loca contraria;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Maldonat com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Math. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>deſertum &amp; penetralia, id eſt conclaue, &amp; intimam maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domus parte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt ſignificaret, quacun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, ratione quo cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> habitu, alius Chriſtus veniret, illi crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non eſſe: vltra de</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A feuer t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donat the Great Ignatia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commenting vpon this place.</note> 
                  <hi>deſerto, &amp; penetralibus quaerere, ſobry non éſt Interpretis. Chriſt</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>hath ſet downe two contrary places for all; to wit the deſert and the penetrals; that is, the parlour and the inmost or moſt reſerued place of the houſe; that hee might ſignifie, in what manner ſoeuer, in what habit ſoeuer, another Christ ſhould come, that hee ſhould not bee beleeued; further to ſeeke and enquire of the deſert and penetrals, is not the part of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Interpreter.</hi> Thus he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the moſt of which his words, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>thoſe, in what manner ſoeuer, in what habit ſoeuer,</hi> and thoſe <hi>another</hi> Chriſt, if they were narrowely ſifted, they would make but little for the Popiſh <hi>Goſpell,</hi> touching the corporall and ſubſtantiall preſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the habits of Bread &amp; Wine; and the maner of his <hi>indiuiſible,</hi> and <hi>diuiſible</hi> preſence: <hi>diuiſible,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe; becauſe euery part of him is really diuided, and diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed each from other; <hi>indiuiſible</hi> in reſpect of the place, where the formes of Bread and wine are; for ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>indiuiſibly totus in toto &amp;c. whole Chriſt, in the whole forme of Bread and euerie part thereof.</hi> Theſe I ſay, and ſuch like, would make nothing for the Popiſh <hi>Goſpel:</hi> but I paſſe by them, and the others; yet I cannot but note thoſe words of his, where hee ſaith, <hi>that it is not the part of a ſober Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, to enquire and examine further of the deſert and pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tralls,</hi> then what his <hi>male-donata</hi> interpretation, his ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen interpretation, hath deuiſed. What is that in <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donat, but conſcientia imbecillitatis, aut peruerſitatis reatus; a verie conſcience of weakenes, or a guilt of peruerſitie?</hi> his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe conſcience well obſeruing, that if theſe words, in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17710:15"/> 
                  <hi>the deſert and the penetralls,</hi> were duely ſifted and ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxally expounded, that then their Popiſh <hi>deſert-pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,</hi> their <hi>boxe-Chriſt adorations,</hi> their <hi>Euchariſt-arke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhips,</hi> would thereby bee called in queſtion, bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted and condemned. But, not regarding this ill-giuen aduice of <hi>Mal-donat</hi> (by interpretation Ill-giuen) I will by <hi>Gods</hi> aſſiſtance, with modeſty beſeeming a Chriſtian, examine theſe words, and their true meaning; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by euince that <hi>Chriſt</hi> by this his prophecie, did ſpecially ayme againſt the Popiſh Idolatry of their teaching him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be in the <hi>deſert &amp; Penetrals</hi> of Bread &amp; wine, and of worſhipping of him in their myſtical <hi>deſerts,</hi> and <hi>penetralls:</hi> &amp; ſo we come to declare, what is meant here by theſe two words, <hi>in Secrets;</hi> (or) <hi>in Penetrals.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In Penetralibus, in Penetralls, in the Secrets.</head>
               <p>I obſerue firſt that the word vſed by <hi>Hutter</hi> in his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew <hi>Math.</hi> is <hi>Hinneh Bahhadarim; Bahhadarim</hi> (of <hi>Cheder</hi>)
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>agninus in the ſauro.</note> the verie <hi>Secrets</hi> or moſt <hi>Secrets.</hi> For this purpoſe, if wee looke into <hi>Pagninus</hi> in his <hi>Treaſurie,</hi> wee ſhall finde him affirming <hi>Cheder</hi> (whence <hi>Bahhadarim</hi>) to ſignifie <hi>aditum, locum prorſus penetralem; the moſt retired parte of anie place.</hi> He addes <hi>ſunt qui putent &amp;c. There are thoſe, who thinke</hi> that the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in Mathew</hi> 24. is expreſſed by this word <hi>Cheder:</hi> againe hee addes his reaſon why the South part of the world is called <hi>Cheder;</hi> to wit, becauſe it is not knowen to vs. Further ſaith hee, <hi>Ben Ezra affirmeth that the Starre which is in the Region of the South, or the corner thereof is called</hi> Cheder; <hi>becauſe thoſe, who dwell in the North cannot, nor doe not, ſee the ſame.</hi> The ſaid <hi>Pagninus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſheweth there largely, that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word <hi>Cheder,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The force of the Hebrew word, ſerueth for our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> is vſed in ſacred Scriptures, to ſignifie the moſt Inmoſt, and moſtretired part of anie place; ſo <hi>Iudges</hi> the 15. and 1. and 16. 9. and <hi>Canti.</hi> 3. 4. to ſignifie the inward part of the bed chamber, to ſignifie the inward places of the <hi>South,</hi> not to bee ſeene nor knowne by vs: ſo, <hi>Iob</hi> 9. 9. and 37. 9. yea more, to ſignifie the inmoſt of mans Soule, the ſecreteſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17710:15"/> part of mans ſpirit: ſo <hi>Pro.</hi> 24. 4. to ſignifie the inmoſt ſecrets of the bellie: ſo <hi>Prouerbs,</hi> 18. 8. the inmoſt parts of death: ſo <hi>Pro.</hi> 7. 27. By which it is moſt manifeſt, that if the force and vigour of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> worde in this place bee followed, the falſe Prophets, which our Sauiour here ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth at, were to teach a preſence of him, ſo ſecret, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, not to be ſeene, that it was onely to be beleev'd and vnderſtood; not ſenſible, but to be beleeu'd; not viſible, but intelligible: and ſo doe the Papiſts. And if it be obiected, that our Sauiour vſed not the Hebrew word but ſpake in <hi>Syriack,</hi> by the <hi>Syriack</hi> word alſo our intent is moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt; for the <hi>Syriack</hi> word <hi>Batauana</hi> may ſignifie the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creteſt of the chamber or the verie <hi>Secret</hi> of the boſome;
<note place="margin">The popiſh prieſts carie Chriſt in the ſecrets of the boſome to hou ſell ther ſicke.</note> a ſecret vſed by the Popiſh Prieſts in England and elſe where, carrying Chriſt in ſmall <hi>pixes, in the verie Secret</hi> of their boſomes to houſell their ſick penitents withall. But ceaſing to adde more, out of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> or <hi>Syriack</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I confeſs I haue no knowledge (for what I herin haue, I had onlie out of <hi>Pagninus</hi> by the direction of my Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Brethren, and learned Friends, Maſter <hi>Salkile</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times an <hi>Ignatian</hi> but now a Religious and learned <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert,</hi> in the Church of England, and alſo from Maiſter <hi>Walker, Parſon</hi> of Saint <hi>Iohn Euangeliſt</hi> in London) I com, to examine, what is meant by the Greeke word vſed in this place.</p>
               <p>Now the Greeke word vſed in this place, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as it makes more effectually &amp; forcibly for our purpoſe; ſo the Greeke edition it ſelfe cannot bee reputed to bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then moſt <hi>Autenticall</hi> and Canonicall by Proteſtant and Papiſt. Our Greeke word then here vſed, is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſocrat. Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> others, vſually take <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for ſecret cellars to put victualls in.</note> Concerning the ſignification whereof, if we make in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie into Greeke Authours, wee ſhall finde that the ſame word hath onely three moſt vſed ſignifications; in all which, the ſame ſerueth ſingularly, for our intent and purpoſe. For firſt it may be taken for a <hi>ſecret</hi> chamber, or cloſe and locked parlour; or ſecondly, for a verie <hi>Ambry,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17710:16"/> Buttery, Saue,</hi> or <hi>Cubbord</hi> to lay victualls in; or, thirdly, for a locked <hi>Cheſt,</hi> or <hi>Cubbord</hi> wherein treaſurie vſually is reſerued. The firſt of theſe the pontificians will not denie: for proofes and declarations of the two later, I will not trouble my ſelfe with alleaging of the teſtimonies of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Authours. The authoritie of <hi>Stephanus,</hi> and <hi>Scaputa</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>; in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: Scapula <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>icon Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o Latinum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> verbo.</hi>
                  </note> after him, with the <hi>Lexicon Greco-Latinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ſet forth at <hi>Lions</hi> in the yeare 1602. ſhall ſuffice. Now <hi>Stephanus</hi> his words are theſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>pro</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>paſsim obu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um, Tameion</hi> for <hi>tamicion is euerie where to bee found in the vſe of Greeke Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours.</hi> Now, that the later is taken in the ſenſe wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and affirme, none ſo ignorant in the <hi>Greeks</hi> as to denie. Againe he ſaith there, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is taken <hi>pro cella panaria et promptuario, for a Saue, Cubbord or Hutch wherein eſculenta et poculenta reconduntur, victualls for eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king are reſerued:</hi> and here-hence it is, that in the vſe of <hi>Greek</hi> Authours the maſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uline word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is taken for a man-butler; the feminine <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for a woman buttler. And thus the ſenſe intended is cleare in the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of Greeke writers; let vs adde a word or two of the latine word vſed in the <hi>vulgar</hi> edition. This word is <hi>penetralibus, Penetrals:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The word <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ibus,</hi> vſed in the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar edition ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies that part which is moſt ſecret.</note> the ſignification whereof euerie ſchoole-boie may be able to deliuer; to wit, that it ſignifies that place or part of place, which is moſt in wardlie in ward, moſt ſecretly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; and, if I may ſo ſpeake, the very <hi>penetration of Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie it ſelfe;</hi> a moſt apt word to ſignifie the <hi>holes and Secrets</hi> wherein '<hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> in our Kingdome hide themſelues, with their ſuppoſed <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from the ſearch of Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, commonly called Purſuiuants.</p>
               <p>This word <hi>penetrale</hi> (ſaith <hi>Calepine</hi>) ſignifieth <hi>omnem partem interiorem domus, vel templi; euerie more inward part</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. in dictio na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o.</note> (not of chamber onelie) <hi>of the houſe or Temple:</hi> here hence it is, that the father of Eloquence calleth thoſe <hi>Gods, diuos</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r. 2. de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trales, Gods Penetrall,</hi> which were worſhipped in the Secrets of the <hi>Temples,</hi> and in lower vaults. Againe; hee
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> cals the hidden and vnſeene fires, <hi>focos Penetrales, Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17710:16"/> ſecret fires,</hi> becauſe moſt inwardly within, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. I ſhall not need to adde more in a point ſo cleare. By this which hath beene deliuered, moſt cleare it is, that our Sauiour intendeth this his prophecie, againſt ſome <hi>falſe</hi>-Chriſts and <hi>falſe-prophets,</hi> who ſhould teach the moſt
<note place="margin">The preſence of Chriſt, which theſe falſe prophets were to teach, was to be moſt ſecret.</note> hidden preſence of him vpon earth that might be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and conſequently for this purpoſe, as it may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably affirmed, he directed the pen of the <hi>Hebrew, Greek Arabick</hi> and <hi>Siriack</hi> writers, yea and of the authour of the <hi>vulgar</hi> edition alſo, to vſe thoſe words, which do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and ſignifie, the moſt ſecret manner of preſence and being that can or may bee thought vpon: ſuch as cannot indeed be conceiued, but onely beleeued; <hi>beleue it not</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>beleeue it not.</hi> And were there euer anie, or can there bee anie, who haue preached, or maie teach, a more my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall preſence, a more hidden, ſecret and obſcure being
<note place="margin">The Authour ſubmits his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation to the Church. vniuerſall.</note> of <hi>Christ,</hi> in <hi>pixes, boxes, cheſts, church-arks,</hi> and <hi>church ſanes,</hi> then the <hi>Papiſts</hi> at this daie doe, and for along time haue done? let others thinke what they pleaſe: for my part (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting my iudgement to the cenſure of <hi>Christs</hi> vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church) I thinke, that our Sauiour in this his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie did ſpecially aime at this point of Popiſh <hi>pſeudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſme.</hi> And to thinke ſo, I am induced by this one
<note place="margin">Chriſt in his prophecie ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh pſeudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſme.</note> reaſon, if I had no other, to wit, that ſeeing the Great and vniuerſall <hi>Antichristian</hi> Synagogue, was to teach and doth teach (to the perdition of innumerable Soules and high contempt of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Maieſtie) a carnall, corporall, continued preſence of Chriſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in lockt cloſets,</hi> in <hi>church-arkes, tabernacles, ſaues, cubbords,</hi> and <hi>coffers,</hi> there to bee beheld and adored, there to be carried and adorned, there to bee trulie praied vnto and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocated,
<note place="margin">De conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rat: diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>go<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Berengarius.</note> there to bee eaten, yea <hi>ſenſibly eaten,</hi> as <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> his Recantation hath it; maie it bee thought, that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo prouident, louing and al-wiſe a ſhepheard of his Church, would in no place haue ſo deteſtable and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable a practice foreſhewed, for the good inſtruction and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17710:17"/> ſafety of his people? Yes, doubtleſs. And where, or when may that more conueniently be done, than in this place, in which ſo many other properties, ſignes and badges, of the great Antichriſtian Synagogue are deſcribed?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A reply with anſwer.</note> If it be replied and ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth indeed in this place foretell a pretended preſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to bee taught by diuers falſe Prophets; but this pretended preſence is not of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, but of the great <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> who ſhall come in his owne name, and deny the true Chriſt: I anſwer; How moſtidle and triuiall muſt this obiection needs be in the iudgement euen of the Pontificians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? who all acknowledge, that <hi>Antichriſts</hi> preſence
<note place="margin">This prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is not to be vnderſtood of any hidde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the great Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt himſelf. <hi>Ribera. viega, in apocal. Bell. l. 3 de Rom. pont. c. 6. 7. 8. Alij.</hi>
                  </note> ſhall be publike and glorious; yea, for three yeeres and a half (the whole time of his durance, as they imagine) moſt triumphant. And if he be <hi>to ſit in the Temple of God, carrying himſelf as if he were a God,</hi> then moſt certainly his preſence ſhall not be in <hi>Secrets</hi> and <hi>Penetrals,</hi> but euen in the very moſt eminent view of the whole world. Let it then reſt proued, that this Prophecy of Chriſt is to be vnderſtood of all ſuch falſe prophets &amp; falſe <hi>anointed ones</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> who, to vſe <hi>Hillaries</hi> phraſe, <hi>ſhall lyingly teach Christ to be in many places; thereby to draw the vexed and afflicted</hi> (hee
<note place="margin">Hill. can. 25. in Mat. apud A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin. in cate. in 24. Mat.</note> meaneth, perſecuted Chriſtians) <hi>into the ſeruice and ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Antichrist.</hi> And is not this that very thing which is in their daily practice; the very <hi>cuppe of abomination,</hi> wherewith they inchant and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull a-ſleep the Princes and Nations of the earth? And, to conclude this point, is not this their <hi>pſeudo-christianiſme,</hi> of teaching true Chriſt to be in their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in their <hi>Tabernacles, Cup-boords,</hi> and <hi>Arks,</hi> the chiefeſt bait wherewith they negotiate the ſoules of the deceiued; the cheefeſt <hi>ſcar-crowe,</hi> whereby they endeauour to affright theirs from coming to vs? for, ſay they, <hi>Behould,</hi> we haue Chriſt truely and in perſonall preſence with vs, vpon our <hi>altars,</hi> and in our <hi>arks:</hi> but they (meaning all reformed Churches) haue nought elſe but a peece of bare leauened bread vpon their profane
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17710:17"/> communion-tables. Wherein they bely vs: for, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches generally do acknowledge a true, reall, ſacramentall preſence of Chriſt, effectually &amp; really wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<note place="margin">Chriſt really preſent by real operation, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough faith in him.</note> by faith in the worthy receiuers. Angels are ſayd truely and really to be, not onely where they definituely are, but alſo where they effectually work: ſo Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is really, not onely in the heauens where it is locally preſent, but alſo in the ſacred myſteries, by the which it worketh effectually and really in the worthy receiuers. And ſo I come to the ful declaration of our ſecond point; to weet, that theſe falſe Prophets, pointed at by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, were not to teach the preſence of the great <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> nor of any other challenging himſelfe to bee <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and denying the true <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord and Sauior <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> but of ſuch who were indeed to teach a ſecret preſence and coming of the true Chriſt himſelf vpon earth, with a <hi>Behould,</hi> beleeue it; <hi>behould, he is in the Secrets.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>He is in the Penetrals: he is, that is, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſon. </seg>Firſt</label> My firſt reaſon I frame out of a double reaſon and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument vſed by our Sauiour, to perſwade and confirme his faithfull againſt the beleeuing of theſe falſe Prophets, and the receiuing of their doctrine. Our Sauiours firſt argument is this: <hi>If they ſhall ſay vnto you</hi> (or thus) <hi>When</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 24. v. 27</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhall ſay vnto you; Behould, Chriſt is in the penetrals or Secrets, beleeue it not. For, as the lightning commeth from the East, and ſhineth vnto the West: ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of man be.</hi> Now, as clear as the heauens it is, that this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<note place="margin">A reaſon that theſe falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers were to teach the true Chriſt himſelf to be in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets.</note> of Chriſt is to bee vnderſtood of a true and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall preſence of himſelf coming in perſon: which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, then our infinitely-wiſe Sauiour (who without blaſphemy cannot be impeacht of impertinent diſcourſe) muſt needs be thought to oppoſe this his publike perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall preſence and comming, againſt all other pretended preſence &amp; comings of him before the ſame; and againſt ſome hidden and ſecret preſence or coming of himſelfe, pretended by theſe falſe Prophets: for, if thus hee ſhould
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17710:18"/> haue ſpoken only againſt ſuch <hi>Hereticks</hi> who would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to haue alone his ſpiritual preſence (by the teaching of his truth) in their Conuenticles; then <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt bee thought thus to haue argued againſt them: If anie falſe Prophets ſhall challenge my truth to bee onely taught by them, and ſo my ſpirituall preſence to be only with them, <hi>beleeue it not. For, as the lightning cometh out of the Eaſt, and ſhineth vnto the Weſt: ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of man bee</hi> publike and apparant. And were not ſuch a manner of arguing moſt vnbefitting the wiſdome of Chriſt? But if wee vnderſtand the falſe doctrine of the falſe Prophets, accordingly as wee haue done of their teaching of Chriſt himſelf coming vpon the earth, and to bee truely and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in the Secrets and penetrals</hi> of <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arks, cheſts,</hi> or <hi>cup-boards,</hi> then our Sauiours reaſon is moſt agreeing and conſequent, thus: When they ſhall ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that I am comne, and that I am in ſuch <hi>Secrets</hi> &amp;
<note place="margin">Chriſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like perſonall coming, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a ſecret perſonall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>penetrals, beleeue it not,</hi> beleeue no ſuch coming of mee. <hi>For, as the lightning cometh out of the Eaſt, and ſhineth vnto the Weſt: ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of man be</hi> publike, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, manifeſt; not ſecret, obſcure or hidden: and vntil I come in ſuch a ſort, look not for me in any other corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall preſence whatſoeuer, And, to meditate a little more on Chriſts ſimilitude, me thinks it is moſt oppoſite to what is profeſſed in the popiſh Synagogue. Chriſt will not come till he come as the <hi>lightning</hi> appearing <hi>from the Eaſt to the Weſt.</hi> The lightning coms ſodenly: but Chriſt in the popiſh Secrets and Penetrals comes expected and looked for at a ſet Inſtant, after the doing of many fooliſh ceremonies. The lightning, as it comes ſuddenly, ſo it ſuddenly diſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> appears: but Chriſt, in the popiſh Secrets, continues and abides ſo long as the formes of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated bread and wine remain; which may be for many years; So in their miraculous <hi>Penetrals</hi> at <hi>Bruxells</hi> and <hi>Mechline.</hi> The lightning is clearly ſeen and obſerued for ſuch: but Chriſt, in the Antichriſtian Secrets, is ſeen no
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17710:18"/> other than <hi>cruſtulum panis, a wafer or round cake of bread,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">So called fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in Rome.</note> or a cup of wine. The lightning, as it is one, ſo in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſame Inſtant it is not ſeen in diuers places: but Chriſt, in the popiſh <hi>Penetrals,</hi> is (to vſe <hi>Hillaries</hi> phraſe) <hi>taught</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hill. in Mat. can. 25</note> 
                  <hi>to be in many pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es;</hi> yea (for, <hi>Hillary</hi> foreſaw not, nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented not, nor preſaged not all) Chriſt is in one and the ſame Church in diuers places, in many Penetrals at once, at one and the ſame very moment.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An objection.</note> But, for further clearing of this matter, it is objected thus: This reaſon of our Sauiour in the 27. verſe, is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely brought by him againſt all ſuch falſe Prophets who ſhould teach a ſecret and hidden comming of him to iudgement; which, the Papiſts doo not: for, they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<note place="margin">De conſecr. diſt. 2. c. Ego Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng. Bell. l. de miſt. 1. c. 12</note> teach a hidden perſonall preſence of him in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; not ſitting there as a Iudge, but being ſet there vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, as in a diſh of the accidents, and ſpecies, or formes, of bread and wine; there to be truely, ſenſibly, eaten and drunk, ſeen and handled.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer, that the words of the falſe Prophets (mentioned by our Sauiour) whereby they enforce their falſe doctrine, doo neither proue nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ince any ſuch thing: nay rather, their teaching of him to be <hi>heer and there,</hi> vp and downe in the <hi>deſert</hi> (that is, as I bouldly interpret forlorn places) <hi>in the Secrets and Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trals,</hi> in <hi>cloſets</hi> (as the Rhemiſts reade it) doth euince, that they meant nothing leſſe; except they may be thought to haue affirmed (and did euer any ſo?) or heerafter to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm (and is it likely that any euer will doo ſo?) that like Biſhops in their viſitations, or Iudges in their circuits, Chriſt (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emoouing vp and downe) ſhould play the Iudgein ſecret chambers, cloſets, &amp;c. O the vanitie of all vanities! once but to dream, that the <hi>pſeudo-chriſtianiſm</hi> of theſe falſe Prophets were ſo to be interpreted.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>A Reply.</label> If they reply, that this reaſon of our Sauiour againſt theſe falſe Prophets, being grounded vpon a publike co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of his into the world, muſt be applied againſt ſuch falſe Prophets who were to teach at leaſt ſome publique
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17710:19"/> coming of him vpon earth before his coming to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which the Papiſts, in the reſpect of this their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of tranſubſtantiatiation, doo not: for, they teach not Chriſt to come into the Sacrament, but to bee there, <hi>vi converſionis, by the force of conuerſion and tranſubſtantiation;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>euch. l. 3. c. 18</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>created</hi> (as ſom ſay) <hi>produced</hi> (as others; ſo my Maiſter in <hi>Rome) adduced or brought</hi> (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) ſo that hee is there indeed, though not by coming thither. O the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious vanity of this reply! To what ſhifting holes are theſe foxes driuen!</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>1</label> I anſwer. Of all the words of theſe falſe Prophets heer mentioned by our Sauiour, there is not one tittle, or jot of word, or circumſtance of Text (ſo wary is Chriſt, that he mentioneth no word, nor circumſtance of time, place or action, that may ſeem to be of himſelf appearing like himſelf, or in the form of men) I ſay, that there is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one word, jot, or tittle of word, which argues expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly either coming, ſtanding, lying, ſitting or walking; but onely that Chriſt is <hi>heer,</hi> that Chriſt is <hi>there,</hi> that Chriſt is in the <hi>deſert</hi> (that is, in forlorne places) that Chriſt is in the <hi>Penetrals, Secrets, Cloſets, &amp;c.</hi> The which, as it is moſt true in the popiſh profeſſion; ſo it is moſt certain in their doctrine, that it may bee done without the proper and perſonall coming of Chriſt: for, they teach, that Chriſt is in the Sacrament by the force of <hi>conuerſion</hi> and <hi>tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntiation.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>2</label> But I anſwer, ſecondly, that if Chriſt were not formerly exiſtent and being in heauen before and when the popiſh Prieſts doo conſecrate; then they might ſeem to ſay (and their ſaying might happely be conceiued and vnderſtood, though moſt falſe) and ſhew how Chriſt ſhould bee there without a proper coming; to weet, by a making or <hi>creation,</hi> as that blaſphemous Saying hath it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Diſcip. de temp. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e. 111. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c. 4. in can. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> See the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, <hi>page 7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The Prieſt is the creator or maker of his Creater;</hi> or by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, as the like impious (if properly and literally ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) Saying hath it, that The Prieſt with his mouth <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit corpus Domini, maketh the body of the Lord, produceth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17710:19"/> the body of the Lord.</hi> But, ſuppoſing that Chriſt is (as the Papiſts themſelues doo confeſſe) in being, and exiſtent in heauen before and when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſing Prieſts doo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate; it is moſt vnimaginable, vnintelligible and incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how hee ſhould bee a-new in the Sactament vpon earth, without a coming or bringing thereto. The which was ſo well vnderſtood by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that (by force of
<note place="margin">Bel. l. 3. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch. c. 18</note> reaſon and truth, vrged thereunto) hee acknowledgeth, that the <hi>conuerſion</hi> wherewith Chriſts body is made pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Sacrament, is to be called <hi>conuerſio adductiua, a conuerſion adductiue, a conuerſion that bringeth Chriſts body,</hi> and conſequently, Chriſt himſelfe, into the Sacrament. Now, if there be a bringing of Chriſt, then there is alſo a coming of Chriſt: except it be ſaid, that Chriſt is brought againſt his will; or that it is one Chriſt which is in the heauens, and another Chriſt which is in the Sacrament: neither of which, I trowe, the Papiſts will dare to affirm. Chriſt then is there in the <hi>Secrets</hi> of bread and wine, and alſo is there by coming: and ſo this reaſon of our Sauior hath his force againſt the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>3</label> Laſtly, I anſwer, that it beeing receiued as a knowne
<note place="margin">Acts 3 <hi>Aug. ep. 57. ad Dardan. &amp; in Ioan. tract. 31 Orig. hom. 33 in Mat.</hi>
                  </note> truth amongſt Chriſtians, profeſſed by euident conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in the Creed, taught by Antients, that Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his aſcenſion was to make no other perſonall and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily coming nor appearance vpon earth, till his coming to iudgement; It is moſt clear, that this reaſon of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours is of force againſt al maner of falſe Prophets what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, who ſhould teach any true corporall preſence of him vpon earth, in what <hi>habite, ſite, form,</hi> or <hi>manner</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer: for, his proof ſtands in this, that hee will neuer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear corporally and preſentially vpon earth, vntil he com <hi>ſuddenly, publikely</hi> and <hi>viſibly,</hi> like the <hi>lightning which ſhineth from the Eaſt, and appeareth vnto the Weſt.</hi> And doth not this make moſt euidently againſt any manner and ſort of Chriſts corporall and perſonall preſence vpon earth, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by any falſe Prophets whatſoeuer; whether it bee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17710:20"/> by comming, or by any other meanes whatſoeuer? But grant, that this firſt reaſon, deliuered in the 27. verſe, bee not ſufficient (if taken alone) yet if wee adioine it to that which follows in the 28. verſe, <hi>Whereſoeuer the body is, there will the Eagles be gathered together,</hi> it will make it moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that our Sauiour, after his glorious aſcenſion, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer intended that his body ſhould be corporally and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially in any place, otherwiſe then ſhould be fitting &amp; agreeing to the viſible glory and perſpicuous majeſty of the ſame. But, to conclude, howſoeuer this reaſon of our Sauiour may bee taken by ſome, yet it proueth moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and certainly, that the falſe doctrine and <hi>pſeudo-chriſtianiſme</hi> of theſe falſe Prophets, of teaching Chriſt to be <hi>heer</hi> and <hi>there,</hi> to bee in <hi>Secrets</hi> and <hi>Penetrals,</hi> is not to bee vnderſtood onely of their challenging of his ſpiritual preſence alone to be with them, and with none but them; but further, of their teaching of ſome corporall manner of Chriſts preſence vpon earth: the which is that verie thing for which I ſpecially doo her enforce the ſame.</p>
               <p>And ſo I come to the confirmation of our reaſon, by our Sauiours ſecond argument, thus; <hi>If therefore they ſhall ſay unto you,</hi> When therfore they ſhal ſay vnto you, <hi>Behold he is</hi> (Chriſt is) <hi>in the penetrals, beleeue it not: for, whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 28.</note> 
                  <hi>the dead body is, thither will the Eagles bee gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Touching which argument of our Sauiour, all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations being ſeriouſly waigh'd; that of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſo. in Mat. 24.</note> with other of the antient and moderne Writers, will bee found more agreeing to truth; to wit, that like as the dead body or carcaſe being ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly expoſed in the field, the eagles do gather themſelues by a naturall inſtinct &amp; ſent, to feed thereon: ſo likewiſe, where hee himſelf ſhould for anie time after his glorious aſcenſion be, he would be in a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and conſpicuous ſort and preſence, in that there ſhould not be wanting multitudes of Angels aſſiſting and miniſtring vnto him. And ſo agreeingly to this ſenſe, our Sauiour inſtructeth his faithful, thus: When the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17710:20"/> ſhall ſaie vnto you that I am in a hidden and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure manner in their ſecrets, and penetrals, as a compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Rats and mice, <hi>beleeue it not:</hi> for my comming and preſence vpon earth, after my glorious aſcenſion, ſhall neuer be but conſpicuous &amp; glorious, neuer without the aſſiſting miniſterie of glorious Angells. And this indeed is ſhewed to be ſo, by ſuch apparitions as are recorded of
<note place="margin">Acts 7. 9.</note> him in the Scriptures. <hi>Stephen</hi> ſawe him, but it was (<hi>the Heauens being opened</hi>) in the glorie of his father: <hi>Saul</hi> ſawe him, yet it was in the ſplendour of his glorie, <hi>in arcanis</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 9. and 2 Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>coelorum, in the palace of Heauen;</hi> where he ſawe ſuch things, which were not to bee vttered. Though the beloued diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple ſawe him; yet it was vpon his throne, in the middeſt of Angells and Saints adoring, and worſhipping him: ſo is Chriſt alwaies attended on, and miniſtred vnto, by the Glorious Eagles. And therefore it is moſt impious, <hi>pſeudo chriſtianiſme,</hi> to place him there, or lyingly to teach him to bee there, in ſuch <hi>ſecrets</hi> and <hi>Penetrals,</hi> where hee ſhall not only bee <hi>ſocius murium et ſoricum; the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Rats and Mice,</hi> but alſo bee their food, for them to feede thereon. And ſo I adioyne my ſecond reaſon for this our principall poynt, in hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſon </seg>Second</label> Our Sauiour in this place, for the fore-inſtruction of his faithful, giueth vnto them certeine cleare and euident ſignes, both of things, practices, and doctrines, which
<note place="margin">Math. 24. 34.</note> which were to happen and to bee in vſe (for the durance of his church) in the antichriſtian Synagogue, before his comming to iudgement, and the conſummation of the world: But ſignes, that they may be profitably ſignificant, muſt bee facill and eaſie to bee vnderſtood. Now if all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſignes in this Chapter, concerning the Antichriſtian Synagogue (their <hi>working of miracles,</hi> their <hi>ſeducing manie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The popiſh practice accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the verie literall ſenſe.</note> their perſecuting, &amp;c.) bee literally to bee vnderſtood; why then ſhall not this their pſeudo-chriſtianiſme of teaching Chriſt to be in <hi>ſecrets</hi> and <hi>Penetralls,</hi> agreeingly to the plaine literall ſenſe of the words, bee taken and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted?</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17710:21"/>
               <p>ſeeing it is a point of ſuch moment concerning the perdition and ſaluation of many Soules. And to adde a confirmation to this reaſon; If theſe words of Chriſt were to bee vnderſtood myſtically againſt the priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles of hereticks chalenging a ſpirituall preſence of him, by reaſon of their teaching of his truth to bee onely with them &amp; among them (which I haue more clearely diſproued aboue) I cannot for my part ſee, what certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for the faithfull's inſtruction, may bee gathered out of the ſame; which yet is the importanteſt, amongſt all the reſt. For as it is moſt euident, by a neuer intermitted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſince Chriſts time, that euery congregation of
<note place="margin">All heretickes arrogate Chriſts ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall preſence. See <hi>Auguſt. Epiſ. 80. ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>. Greg. Moral. 19. cap.</hi> 29. The pureſt Churches in time of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution teach Chriſts ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all preſence in <hi>Secrets.</hi> The <hi>Rhemiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> erroneous po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, to their owne conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> Heretickes and Schiſmatickes, as it challengeth to it ſelfe the power and ſpirituall preſence of Chriſt, ſo it obiecteth to all other, the lacke of the ſame; yea and the moſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Churches of Chriſt himſelf, haue their ebbes and flowes, and then haue beene pureſt when in <hi>cripts, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts,</hi> and <hi>woods</hi> they haue made their aſſemblies; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to preach Chriſt in this ſenſe to bee in <hi>ſecrets,</hi> cannot bee a note or propertie of the Antichriſtian Synagogue, either in the fourth or anie other degree of propertie. The Rhemiſts are moſt eager to interpret this falſe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Chriſts preſence <hi>here and there in Secrets,</hi> and in <hi>Penetralls,</hi> or in <hi>cloſets</hi> (to vſe their owne phraſe) of ſuch Heretikes, as ſhould pretend to tie the Catholicke Church to ſome one place or kingdome: and for this purpoſe they make vpon the 24. of Saint Mathewes Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell this marginall note out of <hi>Auſtine</hi> (a razour where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to cut their own throates) <hi>Whoſoeuer</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin) draweth Chriſt or his Church from the communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de vnit. Eccleſ. cap. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>of all nations chriſtened, to one corner, towne, or Countrie, beleeue him not:</hi> thus <hi>Auſtine</hi> moſt trulie, although not fullie (with due reſpect be it ſpoken) attaining the ſenſe of this place. With what reaſon then are our Pontificians to bee beleeued, who drawe Chriſt, and the Catholicke Church, to one Citie; <hi>to one Mother Cittie</hi> (to vſe Parſons
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17710:21"/> wiſe phraſe) yea to one man, the Pope; whome they make in power, and Authoritie, to be a <hi>vice-Chriſt</hi> or an <hi>Anti-Chriſt,</hi> and vertually to be, and in efficacie to bee the whole Catholike Church. <hi>Nos per eccleſiam intelligimus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſer.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenco <hi>Bellar Tom. 1. pag. 1450.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pontificem Romanum. Wee, by the Church, vnderſtandthe the Pope of Rome, ſaith Gretſer. Which Tyrannicall ſupremacie, and ambitious vniuerſality,</hi> or Catholiciſme of his, becauſe the <hi>Perſian</hi> Chriſtened Churches doe reiect; the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> deteſt; the <hi>Grecian</hi> abhorre; the <hi>Egyptian</hi> loath; the <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couian</hi> execrate, euen as the diuell himſelfe; the <hi>Arabian</hi> ſcorne; the <hi>Armenian</hi> condeme; all reformed Churches hate &amp; accurſe; for this cauſe they are, by the holie father and his, reputed for Heretickes, and Reprobate Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; by him whoſe hands <hi>Eſau</hi>-like are againſt all, as the hands of all ought to be againſt him: and ſo, in true Chriſtian wiſedome, and policie are, except where hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie ouer-aboundes; or elſe, where God, for ſome other
<note place="margin">The yoke of Poperie.</note> greeuous ſinnes, may intend to bring in <hi>iugum exactoris,</hi> the yoke of the Exactour &amp; Oppreſſour vpon a ſtiffenec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked people, or generation: and ſo I adde my third princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall reaſon.</p>
               <p>My third reaſon I deduce, out of the <hi>Energie</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of certaine other words, here vſed by our Sauiour. I obſerue the Aduerb <hi>Behould,</hi> twice repeated: which, as it is an Aduerb of admiration; ſo it is alwaies demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and ſpecializing of ſome ſingular matter, requiring regard and conſideration. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> in thoſe words
<note place="margin">Iohn 1. 36.</note> of his, <hi>Behould the lambe of God,</hi> did demonſtrate Chriſt, to his diſciples, to bee admired and followed: ſo theſe
<note place="margin">An argument from the ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of certaine words.</note> falſe prophetts, by their behold hee is in the <hi>Penetrals,</hi> doe inuite the faithfull to behould and beleeue on Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a hidden &amp; obſcure manner in ſuch penetrals: and doe not the Papiſts ſo? I alſo weigh, the Aduerbs <hi>here</hi> and <hi>there;</hi> which euer doe deſigne, ſome ſpeciall circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of place; as thoroughoutthe Scriptures is manifeſt. And if to them wee adioine the ſpecialties of the places
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17710:22"/> (the <hi>deſert,</hi> and the <hi>penetrals</hi>) with the Pronowne (hee) in the third perſon, demonſtrating a ſingular perſon, whereof ſpeech was made, or intended immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and withall adde the Verb Subſtantiue (is) affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; together with the Inteiection (in) deſigning; <hi>he is in the Penetrals</hi>) my intent will more manifeſtly appear, that theſe falſe prophets were to teach, the true Chriſt himſelfe to bee in ſuch <hi>penetrals of boxes, cubbords, arkes, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, Saues, Promptuaries,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Againe: I obſerue; hee is not, Chriſt is not, taught by theſe falſe prophets to bee in anie one onely ſingle place or ſecret alone; but ioyntly, and at the ſame time, hee is taught to bee <hi>here and there;</hi> in the <hi>deſerts,</hi> in the <hi>Secrets.</hi> They ſay not, in the Singular number, in <hi>penetrali,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in ſome one ſecret, one penetral; but, in the <hi>ſecrets,</hi> in cloſets: yea, all readings and Tranſlations (the <hi>Hebrew, Siriack, Arabick, Greek, Latine, Engliſh, French Dutch, &amp;c.</hi>) haue the word in the Plurall number; all of them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by demonſtrating, that theſe falſe-prophets were to teach Chriſt to be at once and at one &amp; the ſame time in diuers <hi>Secrets, Penetrals,</hi> Cloſets, Arkes, Cubbords. Yea, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabick word ſignifieth fallacious and deceptious places, in the Plurall number. All which is done with ſuch an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite confuſion in the Popiſh Churches, that we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly inueigh againſt them, that not onely according to the number of their temples, and altars, they haue mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied the the Preſences of Chriſt; but alſo, that for euery perſon, and profeſſing member of their Church, they haue once (or more often) in the yere, Chriſt corporally, perſonally, and ſubſtantially preſent in ſome ſecret or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of Arks, Altars, Tabernacles, Cubbords, Cloſets &amp;c. to bee beheld (<hi>behould hee is heer,</hi> behould hee is in this <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret,</hi> behould hee is in that ſecret) to bee beheld I ſay, ſeene and adored. And this is done ſo punctually by them, that as the like was neuer done by anie other ſince Chriſt his time; ſo neither is it imaginable or conceiueable, how
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17710:22"/> anie falſe-prophets for anie time to come ſhall, may, or can more punctually, fully and compleately, act and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame.</p>
               <p>Againe: I note and obſerue that our Sauiour tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth theſe falſe-prophets (who were to teach ſuch a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious and prodigious preſence of him in <hi>Secrets</hi>) to be <hi>pſeudo-Chriſts, falſe-Chriſts, falſe-anointed ones: falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anointed ones,</hi> I ſay. And doth not Chriſt, in this his tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and appellation of them, deſigne to vs the verie Popiſh maſſing prieſts? who (and onely who) for their powerfull conſecrating and making of him to bee ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in <hi>Secrets,</hi> are ſuperſticiouſly anointed in their hands and fingers all ouer: yea their <hi>altar-ſtones</hi> whereon, their <hi>Chalices</hi> wherein, their <hi>Patins</hi> wherevpon, Chriſt is to be conſecrated, and made to bee in ſuch <hi>ſecrets,</hi> are not to bee reputed fit and apt for the ſame purpoſe, except they be firſt <hi>anointed:</hi> and, being <hi>anointed,</hi> they are ſo ſacred, that the vnanointed hands of the Laick may not touch them, without great offenſe. Neither can it bee replied and ſaid, that theſe falſe-anointed-ones (mentioned by our Sauiour in the 24. verſe) are thoſe verie Chriſts, which ſhall bee pretended to bee in <hi>Secrets.</hi> For it is moſt euident by the Text, and Saint <hi>Hillaries</hi> interpretation, with <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philact</hi> and others, that theſe falſe Chriſts are to bee the verie ſame with the falſe proprets who were to bee pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and in publike to preach a ſecret preſence of the true Chriſt; yea, and for confirmation of the ſame, were to doe ſuch miracles, <hi>that if it were poſsible the verie elect ſhould bee in danger to bee ſeduced,</hi> and drawne into errour. Thus we obſerue how all circumſtances, and the energie of all the words concur to our purpoſe againſt this point of Popiſh <hi>pſeudo-Chriſtianiſme.</hi> And ſo ceaſing to adde more in this place (wherof more anone) I com to annect my fourth reaſon; which is thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">reaſon </seg>Fourth</label> Theſe falſe Prophets were to teach a ſecret preſence of ſome one called Chriſt. Now this muſt needes bee either
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17710:23"/> Antichriſt, the Great one himſelf; or elſe ſome other petty falſe Chriſts, challenging themſelues to be the true Chriſt; ſuch, as <hi>Theudas</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> of <hi>Galilie</hi> were of ould in <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie;</hi> and ſuch as <hi>George Dauid</hi> was of late in <hi>Germanie,</hi> and <hi>Hacket in England;</hi> elſe they muſt bee ſuch, as will falſely teach of the true Chriſt himſelfe, that hee is in ſuch <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets and Penetrals.</hi> The firſt cannot ſtand. For, the Great
<note place="margin">This preſence cannot be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie petty Anti-Chriſts.</note> 
                  <hi>Antichriſts</hi> preſence or rather reigne and kingdome ſhall bee moſt publike, viſible, and glorious. Neither can the ſecond conſiſt. For, in what daunger of perdition can the Elect bee by the preaching of ſuch pettie, and moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious <hi>Chriſtlings;</hi> ſuch, as <hi>George Dauid,</hi> and <hi>Hacket</hi> were? neither did theſe euer anie wonders. The prophecie then, muſt of neceſſitie bee vnderſtood of ſome falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who were to teach a ſecret preſence of the true Chriſt in the <hi>Great Anti-christian Synagogue,</hi> as I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued aboue. And this is alſo cleared, by that of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in <hi>Saint Luke</hi> 17. 22. 23. 24. where hee ſheweth, that theſe falſe-prophets would pretend to ſhewe <hi>the ſonne of man himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this purpoſe, <hi>Theophilact</hi> writeth thus; <hi>Si venerint in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theophil. in 24. Math.</note> 
                  <hi>Impoſtores &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If Impoſtors ſhall come, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt is com, but is in the deſert, or is hid in ſome houſe, or in the promptuarie and cellar of the ſame; or in the more inward</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note theſe words of <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilact, more in ward parts;</hi> then, <hi>promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary or cellar. Theophilact</hi> fore ſawe part of this point of popiſh pſeudo-Chriſtianiſme.</note> 
                  <hi>places of it; bee not deceiued; for the comming of Chriſt ſhall not need any one to ſhewe the ſame; for it ſhall bee manifeſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all; euen as the lightning is:</hi> thus hee. Which his words I bring not to proue fully my intent (for <hi>Theophilact</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing before tranſubſtantiation was decreed, and before Chriſts ſuch ſecret preſence in <hi>penetrals,</hi> was generally taught; no maruell that hee did not fully attaine the ſenſe of the prophecie) but, I produce his ſaying, for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe onely, to proue that the falſe-prophets doctrine is to be vnderſtood of a ſecret preſence of the true Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in <hi>ſecrets,</hi> and in the <hi>deſert.</hi> And ſo wee proceed to our fift reaſon: which is the cleere fulfilling of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17710:23"/> according as we vnderſtand it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>5</label> A Prophecy, vntill it be fulfilled (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly)
<note place="margin"> 5. <hi>Iren. l. 4. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntra haereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: 43</hi>
                  </note> is as a riddle, or a book ſealed: but, beeing once ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, it is no longer a hidden, but a manifeſt truth, an open reuelation. Now, it is as cleare as the heauens, that this Prophecy of Chriſt, beeing vnderſtood accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the plain ſenſe of the words, and accordingly as I haue taken the ſame, is fully and moſt clearly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in the <hi>Roman Synagogue:</hi> of whoſe religion it is a prime myſtery, To teach Chriſt <hi>to be heer and there in the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſt himſelf perſonally taught to be heer in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of popiſh churches, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, cloſets, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Secrets and Penetrals</hi> of their <hi>Churches, Chappels</hi> and <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories,</hi> and to particularize in ſome. For this cauſe they cry out, <hi>Behould, he is daily <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in the cubbords, arks and tabernacles,</hi> of our Churches: <hi>Behould, he is, on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Good-friday and Mandie-thurſday, in the Secrets &amp; Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrals of our ſepulchres:</hi> Behould, he is frequently in the Secrets of the boſomes of our Prieſts, and of the pixes; yea, and of the pockets alſo ſometimes of our Prieſts: Behould, he is day by day in the Secrets of bread &amp; wine, vpon our <hi>Altars;</hi> and this with ſuch a confuſion, that the blinde <hi>Suppliant,</hi> finding himſelf in ſome one Church
<note place="margin">Chriſt eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in diuers places in one church, at one and the ſame moment.</note> where at one and the ſame time diuers Maſſes are ſaid, and conſequently Chriſt in diuers places made and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated, he cannot well tell to which <hi>Altar</hi> he ſhould turn himſelf: for, if his face bee humbly bowed to him vpon one altar; his back, &amp;c. muſt needs bee irreuerently tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned towards him vpon another altar; Chriſt is ſo vp and downe, <hi>heer and there,</hi> vpon their diuerſe altars. I will not ſay, <hi>O ſanctas Gentes! O holy Nations!</hi> but I bouldly inueigh, <hi>O ſtultas Gentes! quibus talia naſcuntur ab altari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus numina: O moſt fooliſh peoples, who haue ſtore of gods ſo growing and multiplying vpon their altars!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heer I cannot omit (it is ſo agreeing to our purpoſe) to ſpeak of their miraculous &amp; prodigious Hoſts at <hi>Brux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Iac. Suar.</hi> his <hi>Theſ. qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drag. ſer. 42. in fer. 2. do. pal.</hi> The papiſts miraculous hoſtes (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ored) at <hi>Brux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, Mechlin,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Naples, Mechlines,</hi> and elſewhere. How euident is it, that this Antichriſtian note, <hi>Behould, hee is</hi> (Chriſt is) in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17710:24"/> 
                  <hi>penetrals,</hi> is fulfild in them; when-as they pretend to keep Chriſt in ſuch miraculous Hoſtes, faſt lockt vp at theſe places? where they alſo doo often, with a Behold hee is heer, Behold, hee is in the Penetrals, inuite their blinde and ſuperſtitious people to behould and worſhip him: at which fond and idolatrous ſuperſtition, I my ſelf haue been ſomtimes a ſuperſtitious Suppliant. But, it is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to obſerue with what acclamations the ignorant ſort, crying <hi>miſericordia, miſericordia, mercy, mercy, mercy,</hi> doo
<note place="margin">The phrenzie of popiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</note> there and then adore and inuocate this their Chriſt. Hee is there then with them in <hi>Penetrals, beheld, beleeued,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored and inuocated: and what more can the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſay or doo, then that which theſe falſe Prophets do require?</p>
               <p>Neither can it ought auail theſe falſe Prophets for their teaching of Chriſt his corporall preſence in ſuch places, that (as they ſay) vpon theſe their miraculous Hoſtes, drops of blood doo appear. For, if it be ſo (which I my
<note place="margin">A difficulty concerning the pretended drops of blood in their miraculous hoſtes at <hi>Brux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,</hi> &amp;c.</note> ſelfe could neuer perfectly diſcern) then I demand of the learnedeſt <hi>Ignatian</hi> and <hi>Pontifician,</hi> whether thoſe dry drops of blood, appearing in thoſe miraculous Hoſtes, be true drops of Chriſts naturall blood, or not. If ſo (as many of them ſay, and alſo ſay that euery drop of Chriſts blood was hypoſtatically vnited to the deity) what then will they ſay to that true principle of Diuinity, venerable for antiquity, receiued alſo by themſelues, that <hi>Quod</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aqum. 3. q. 5. 2 &amp; 6 a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. 5</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſtus ſemel aſſumpſit nunquam dimiſit, What Chriſt once aſſumpted to himſelf</hi> (by hypoſtaticall vnion) <hi>hee neuer left the ſame.</hi> What? will they ſay that the ſame vnion is diſſolued? or will they ſay, that by the meanes of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of bread and wine, they are ſtill vnited to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninity? That were a dream. Or will they ſay, that like as Chriſt, becauſe he was ouer-amorous of <hi>Catharine</hi> of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennas</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Sienna</hi> her life.</note> heart (as it is deſcribed in her life) did change his owne heart with hers, and for hers; and for that purpoſe did make and vnmake hypoſtatical vnions and aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17710:24"/> ſo likewiſe, to ſatisfie their ſuperſtitious humours, is content to part with ſome drops of his owne pretious blood, and to let them hang in the air for their worſhips<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancies to behould, adore and admire? Or will they ſay, that theſe drops were neuer by hypoſtaticall vnion vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the deity? Whatſoeuer they ſay, they are taken in their folly, or put to deny that which otherwiſe they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally teach, that Chriſts blood, and euery drop thereof, was hypoſtatically vnited to the diuinity. If they ſay that theſe ſeeming drops of blood are not true blood indeed; then let them withall admit, that ſuch mendacious ſignes are no other than lying wonders of falſe Prophets: and why then doo they admit their people to adore, worſhip and inuocate, Chriſtin the ſame?</p>
               <p>Againe; to note another of their <hi>penetrals,</hi> in which they ſay, <hi>Behould, Chriſt is.</hi> So <hi>Luciferian</hi>-like and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable hath the pride of ſome of their holy Fathers beene, that, when they haue remooued from one place to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they command a conſecrated <hi>Hoſte,</hi> that is, true Chriſt (in their faith) to be put into a <hi>tabernacle</hi> or a little <hi>arke,</hi> made for the purpoſe; and the ſame to be ſet vpon a horſe or mules back; and ſo, like a <hi>Iohn praecurſor,</hi> or a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>running <hi>Apparitor,</hi> to be ſent away, and to precede before their <hi>ſanctities.</hi> O <hi>Idolatrie</hi> of <hi>Idelatries!</hi> O contempt of Chriſtin the higheſt degree! An Idolatry, worſe than that of the <hi>Mexicans,</hi> adoring in a Round of Proceſſions the fleſh and bones of their god <hi>Vitzill-puitzil,</hi> made to them
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Boterus</hi> his v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>part. 4. l. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> of dough, and conſecrated with popiſh-like charmes O the impious ſcorn of Chriſts Majeſty! Chriſt, ſhut vp in a <hi>penetrall,</hi> is carried before as a <hi>vicar</hi> of his owne <hi>vicar:</hi> but his Holineſſe is publikely mounted, to be adored by all paſſers by. Chriſt is carried before, attended on by the meaner train: but his Holineſſe comes after, attended on by Prelates and Nobles. Chriſt is ſet on a mules or horſes back: but his Holineſſe is ſometimes mounted on mens ſhoulders. Chriſt is in <hi>penetrals,</hi> and ſo called vpon by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17710:25"/> thoſe who may hear and regard the ſound of the little bell crying and ſounding out, <hi>Behould, he is heer:</hi> his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is called vpon by all; and, out of the treaſurie of Chriſts merits (carried in the box) he beſtowes a bleſſing of an <hi>Indulgence</hi> and pardon vpon all. Loe then, how Chriſt is <hi>heer</hi> in a <hi>Penetral;</hi> and Antichriſt alſo is heer, but not in a penetrall, but ſitting <hi>in the Temple, or againſt the Temple, carrying himſelf as if he were a God;</hi> yea more, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2</note> aboue God, if Chriſt, whom they pretend to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in a Penetrall, bee their God: for, moſt manifeſt it is, that Chriſt in ſuch perambulations is leſſe reſpected than
<note place="margin">Chriſt leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected than the pope.</note> the Pope.</p>
               <p>Further (which paſſeth all admiration) they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to teach, that he is (Chriſt is) in the penetrall of a dung-hill, if a conſecrated Hoſte chance (as it hath been
<note place="margin">Spec. mag. exem.</note> done) to be caſt therein; yea, to be in the <hi>Secret</hi> or <hi>Cloſet;</hi> yea (more) to bee in the very hands of the <hi>Coniurer,</hi> and
<note place="margin">Benno card. in vita Greg. 7</note> by him to be ſo preſented as a ſweet-ſmelling ſacrifice to <hi>Beel-zebub:</hi> which that it hath been done, or may be don, their Learned will not deny; and that it was done by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeauenth, <hi>Benno</hi> the Cardinall conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmeth in his life. Again: he is or may be in the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrals of a <hi>Flie,</hi> if ſhe (as it hath been done) ſip of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated chalice. He is in the Penetrall of a <hi>mouſe or rat,</hi> if they eat of a conſecrated Hoſte, which often (and who knowes how often?) hath been done. I might bee infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite. And are not theſe idolatrous fopperies, well-beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and worthy of the Antichriſtian Synagogue? O ye heauens, bee ye deſolated; and the gates thereof, bee ye aſtoniſhed. Was there euer ſuch a <hi>tranſubſtantiating</hi> of bread and wine into Chriſt, before <hi>The Man of ſinne</hi> drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thereof; and thereby ſet vp his god <hi>Maozim</hi> to be worſhipped in turrets? and yet they are not aſham'd ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and yet they are not confounded nor confuſed for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Venerable Antiquity, becauſe ſhee knew that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17710:25"/> of our Lords Supper was a Sacrament onely whil'ſt in vſe, and then moſt honourable, religious and venerable; did for this cauſe either burn, or cauſe young children to conſume and eat vp, ſuch relickes of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated bread and wine which were left after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: the later is witneſſed by <hi>Euagrius;</hi> for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
<note place="margin">Euagr. l. 4. luſt. c. 35 I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch. com. in Leuit.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or <hi>Origen</hi> is witnes vpon <hi>Leuiticus.</hi> But theſe <hi>Chriſt-m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kers</hi> doe reſerue him in <hi>Penetrals</hi> &amp; <hi>Cheſts,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and cry out, ſaying, <hi>Behould, hee is heer,</hi> come and ſee: <hi>Beheld, he is there,</hi> go and worſhip: <hi>Come, let vs fall downe and kneel before the Lord our Maker.</hi> And is not this <hi>Idolatry</hi> in the higheſt degree?</p>
               <p>Our moſt <hi>drad Soueraign,</hi> in that moſt learn'd <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reg. praemonit. p 48. 49</note> of his, hath in abomination the intolerable adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Images</hi> vſed in popiſh Churches, though the ſame
<note place="margin">The papiſts flat Idolatry.</note> adoration be pretended by them to be giuen to the <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> for the <hi>Prototyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns</hi> ſake, that is, for reſpect to God or to the Saints, whoſe <hi>Images</hi> they are. And there hee alſo moſt learnedly proues, their ſame adoration of <hi>images</hi> &amp; <hi>reliques</hi> to be impious and <hi>idolatrous.</hi> But loe heer a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er point of <hi>Idolatrie:</hi> the very adoration of Chriſt due to him in perſon, is giuen to Chriſt vpon an imagined and mendacious pretended preſence of him in the <hi>Penetrals</hi> of bread and wine. <hi>Lo, he is in the Penetrals,</hi> ſay the falſe Prophets: but Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Beleeue it not.</hi> And if they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore, commit they not in ſo dooing <hi>Idolatrie</hi> in the higheſt degree? Is not he an <hi>Idolater</hi> who worſhippeth God in a pebble ſtone, or in a <hi>ſtatue</hi> of ſtone; though God, by the immenſity of his <hi>all-preſence</hi> bee in the ſaid ſtatue? Shall not hee then bee an <hi>Idolater,</hi> who ſhall vpon a pretended falſe preſence worſhip Chriſt in the formes of bread and wine, in the <hi>Penetrals</hi> of a <hi>Church-ark</hi> or <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> where he indeed is not? What is <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> if this be not, To wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and to adore a nothing of Chriſt for Chriſt; to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore bread and wine in ſtead of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>The Iſraelites were impious Idolaters, though they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17710:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17710:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17710:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17710:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17710:28"/> worſhipped the God of Iſrael in the <hi>golden Calf,</hi> and yet
<note place="margin">Exodus 32</note> God by his immenſity was in the <hi>golden Calf: Idolatrous</hi> likewiſe are theſe men, who pretend to adore Chriſt in <hi>penetrals,</hi> where he is not; and where he would not bee reputed to be: <hi>Beleeue it not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heer in this place I cannot pretermit to declare, how aptly this word <hi>penetals (hee is in the penetrals)</hi> is vſed for the popiſh maner of teaching Chriſts beeing vnder the <hi>Secrets</hi> of bread and wine. The popiſh <hi>prieſts</hi> are not ſo powerfull for the making of their Chriſt preſent in the <hi>Secrets</hi> of bread and wine, as the popiſh Diuines are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<note place="margin">How Chriſt is diuiſibly and indiuiſibly preſent in the popiſh Secrets.</note> for the opening and declaring of the manner how hee is there, to weet, by a kinde of penetration: <hi>Totus in toto, &amp; totus in qualibet parte; whole Chriſt in the Secret of the whole Hoste, and whole Chriſt in the Secret of euery the leaſt particle of the Hoſte.</hi> But let vs conſider a-little, how they explicate this and endeauour to auoid that penetration (of Chriſt in himſelfe) which I object vnto and againſt them.</p>
               <p>Diuerſe of the antienter <hi>ſchool-ſophiſters</hi> haue dared to
<note place="margin">See <hi>Holcot, in 4. q. 3. Biel in 4 diſt. 1. q. 1. not. 3. &amp; lec. in can. 37</hi>
                  </note> teach; that, if Maſſe had been celebrated in diuerſe places at that very time when Chriſt ſuffred, he ſhould haue bin crucified in ſo many places: but this poſition little plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the
<note n="*" place="margin">So my maſter <hi>Vaſqu.</hi> in <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> tranſubſtantiating <hi>Theologues</hi> of theſe times, who teach the clean contrary. Becauſe, ſay they, though Chriſt bee in the Sacrament moſt really, truely and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally, and hath his dimenſions of quantity, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of parts (to wit, an arm of ſuch a length, a hand of ſuch a breadth, &amp;c.) <hi>in ordine ad ſe, in reſpect of himſelf or to himſelf;</hi> ſo that where his head is, there his foot is not, and ſo of the reſt: yet in reſpect of the place in which hee is, and in regard of the accidents of bread and wine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which he is, hee hath no parts nor dimenſions, one without other; but is like the ſoule of man indiuiſibly <hi>totus in toto, &amp; totus in qualibet parte, whole Chriſt indiuiſibly in the Secret of the whole Hoſte, and whole Chriſt in the ſecret
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17710:28"/> of euery leaſt particle of the Hoſte:</hi> and conſequently, Chriſt being th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re <hi>indiuiſibly,</hi> is alſo there <hi>impaſſibly,</hi> not ſubject to any hurt or corruption: the which how can it bee i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined to be, without true penetration of Chriſts parts and members one within another? O moſt horrible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and fearfull commixtion of Chriſt! And this is confirmed by that which they ſecretly teach, yea, which they publikely read in their Schools (for, ſo did my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Gabriel <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſques,</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi>) to weet, that by reaſon of
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gabriel Vaſqu.</hi> his paradox touching Chriſts maner of preſence.</note> this indiuiſible preſence of Chriſt in the <hi>Hoſte,</hi> when any of their Deuouts doo behould a conſecrated <hi>Hoſte,</hi> they may (as it ſhall beſt fit their deuotion) imagine and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Chriſt to be there in what faſhion they ſhall pleaſe; either as a perfect (yea, bloody) man as hee was hanging vpon the Croſſe, or as a young pretty babe as hee was in his mothers arms; and this, in what ſite and diſpoſition of body as they ſhall liſt, either ſitting, ſtanding or lying, with eies open or ſhut, with hands cloſed or open; and ſo <hi>in infinitum,</hi> as there may be different manners and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions of ſtill and ſilent geſtures in man.</p>
               <p>This is their moſt prodigious poſition: which is ſo flat
<note place="margin">A prodigious poſition of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <hi>Theologues</hi>
                  </note> againſt all truth of Diuinity, and light of Philoſophy, as it euidently followes out of that main and vain doctrine of theirs, that <hi>Chriſt is wholly and truely, after the manner of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bell. de Sacram. euch. l. 4. c. 21. &amp; 22. &amp; l. 3. c. 4. 5</note> 
                  <hi>a ſpirituall ſubstance, indiuiſibly in the whole imagined ſpace and place of the conſecrated Hoſte, and euery part or least parcel of the ſame:</hi> ſo it alſo moſt euidently ſhewes, that Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſts body doth not onely, by the true dimenſion of the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iac. Suar.</hi> in his <hi>theſ. quadra. in ſer. 42. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er. 3. do. pal.</hi> hath a compariſon of an egge readie for the hatch of a chicken, where nothing is to be ſeen but whitenes, &amp;c of Chriſt in the hoſt. Read this his Sunilitude; which he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a fit one.</note> thereof, penetrate the quantity of the bread &amp; wine (which in their doctrine remains after conſecration) but further alſo it clearly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uinceth all the parts and members of Chriſts body to penetrate and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſedly to pearce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to each other. And what a <hi>phantaſticall</hi> and <hi>paradoxicall</hi> body haue we heer? hauing in it ſelf, and in reſpect of it ſelf, all proportions and dimenſions of bodily parts, with their due <hi>longitude, latitude</hi> and <hi>thicknes;</hi> but, in reſpect of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17710:29"/> the imagined place, of bread and wine, without all theſe; and yet withall, in reſpect of the ſaid place and imagined ſpace, the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>out meditator may take Chriſts bodie to bee truly in ſuch forme and faſhion, either as of a perfect man, or as of a little Child, as ſhall moſt agree with his fancie. <hi>O Egregions and Acute Rabbies.</hi> Theſe, and of this <hi>claſs,</hi> bee the <hi>worthies,</hi> which ſome vnſtable miniſters for want of better ſtuffe, vſe to cite in their Sermons. And is not this <hi>Penetrall</hi> (penetrall by penetration) wherein Chriſt is taught perſonally to bee and reſide, that which our Sauiour here hath in ſuch deteſtation; <hi>Beleeue it not?</hi> Let others thinke what they pleaſe: I cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe reſolue, but that it is the verie ſame which he here fore-telles and condemnes, <hi>If therefore they ſhall ſay vnto you behould hee is in the Secrets beleeue it not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt what hath beene proued, it is thus obiected:
<note place="margin">A difficult ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection as it may ſeeme; yet eaſilie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> firſt, Chriſt foretelleth of ſome <hi>Pſeudo-Chriſts and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prophets,</hi> who ſhould teach him to bee preſent amongſt men, &amp; conuerſant with them, in humane ſhape, though in ſecret <hi>cloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts,</hi> or in the <hi>deſert:</hi> but ſo doe not the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> For, they onely teach Chriſt to bee (though perſonally, yet) not in humane ſhape, but <hi>ſacramentally,</hi> inuiſibly, and indiuiſibly, vnder the formes, and in the ſecrets, and <hi>penetrals</hi> or entrailes (if I may ſo ſpeak) of the <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this Obiection I anſwer diuerſe waies; and each of
<note place="margin">A cleare three fould anſwer.</note> them ſufficient. Firſt, our Sauiour (if wee inſiſt vpon his expreſſe words, and take them literally, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doe thoſe words, <hi>this is my bodie</hi>) ſpeaketh nothing at all touching his pretended conuerſation in humane ſhape amongſt men: neither doth hee vtter anie word, by which the ſame may bee gathered, but rather, the cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie; vſing the words, <hi>penetrals, deſert</hi> &amp;c. neuer ſo much as mentioning anie <hi>town, citie,</hi> or ſpecial <hi>Kingdome,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſhall pretend Chriſt to bee; nor glancing in anie tearms or words at anie kinde of humane actions (of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17710:29"/> ſpeech, ſight, viſible, apparent &amp;c.) which theſe falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets will pretend: but hee onlie foretelleth his faithfull, that they ſhould bee inuited to ſee him in the <hi>penetrals;</hi> and this not in anie humaneſhape, but in ſome ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<note place="margin">Theſe falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phets were not to ſhew Chriſt in any humane ſhape.</note> ſort, as would require faith for the perfecting of the ſaid ſight of him. And in this reſpect it is, that Chriſt ſaith <hi>beleeue it not:</hi> hee doth not ſay beleeue him not; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not him; <hi>but beleeue it not;</hi> or <hi>beleeue not it: It.</hi> So that, it is a <hi>it,</hi> a myſticall and myſterious <hi>it</hi> and manner of Chriſts being <hi>ſacramentally</hi> &amp; <hi>perſonally,</hi> in ſuch <hi>Secrets</hi> and <hi>penetrals,</hi> but not a hee, or a him, of Chriſts being there in humane ſhape. Which being ſo, that theſe <hi>falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prophets,</hi> were to inuite the faithfull, beleeuingly with faith to <hi>behould Chriſt to bee</hi> perſonally <hi>in ſuch Secrets;</hi> I hope the Papiſts will not denie but the ſame is punctually acted in their Chriſt, in their <hi>Secrets, Cloſets, Church-arks, Church-cupbords, tabernacles, &amp;c. Parſons</hi> was ſo well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Parſons</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Reports cap. 10. pag. 236.</note> of the truth of this, that Chriſt is to bee beheld, and ſeene in the Secrets of Bread and Wine, that with great ioie and confidence, hee relateth out of <hi>Walſingham</hi> the anſwere of <hi>King Henrie</hi> the 3. of <hi>England,</hi> made to King <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> called the <hi>Saint:</hi> For, whereas King <hi>Lewis</hi> ſaid, that hee had rather heare manie Sermons then many maſſes; King <hi>Henrie</hi> replied, and ſaid; that, for his part, he had rather heare many maſſes then manie
<note place="margin">A conference betwixt King <hi>Henrie</hi> the 3. of <hi>England</hi> &amp; King <hi>Lewis</hi> called the Saint.</note> Sermons, and withall yeeldeth this reaſon for the ſame; that hee had rather ſee his friend then heare anye man, though neuer ſo eloquently diſcourſing of him. Chriſt then is to bee ſeene in popiſh <hi>penetrals,</hi> with a <hi>Behould,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring faith and admiration.</p>
               <p>If they ſhould ſay and reply that they ſee him not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, that cannot bee: for, ſtanding within their owne
<note place="margin">Chriſt in the popiſh <hi>Secrets v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> conuerſions</hi> by the force and <hi>Energie</hi> of conuerſion.</note> principles, that Chriſt is there <hi>vi conuerſionis by the vertue of conuerſion</hi> (as my maſter <hi>Vaſques</hi> taught in <hi>Rome</hi>) I dare vndertake to ſhewe, that in regard of the dependencie &amp; ſuſtentation which the accidents of bread haue from the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17710:30"/> bodie of Chriſt, &amp; whereby the ſubſtance of bread ceaſes to be, and is turned into the bodie of Chriſt, there is as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
<note place="margin">So my Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Vaſquez</hi> his <hi>dictates,</hi> which I haue with mee.</note> an vnion betwixt the accidents of bread and wine and Chriſts body, as there is betwixt mans Soule, and the qualities ſubſtantiall of the bodie; yea in a degree (though of farre inferiour excellencie) of like kinde, the accidents of bread and wine are ſuſtained or ſuſtentated (if I may ſo ſpeake) by the bodie of Chriſt, as the <hi>Humanitie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The bodie of Chriſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tames the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of bread &amp; wine.</note> of Chriſt is ſuſtained &amp; ſubſiſteth by the diuine <hi>ſubſiſtence:</hi> the difference onelie is; one is more excellent then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Againe: in the one, is ſupplied a naturall <hi>ſubſiſtence;</hi> in the other, a naturall <hi>inexiſtence</hi> or <hi>inherencie:</hi> Now then; as man in regard of outward qualities may be ſaid to bee ſeen, or the ſonne of God may be ſaid to be ſeen, although
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes that by conſecration Chriſts bodie is made true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and viſibly preſent. <hi>Bellar. lib. 1. de Miſſ. cap. 12. ¶. Reſtat. Salmero. in vita. Bellar. lib. 2. de Euchar. cap. 24. Auguſt. lib. 3. de Trinit. cap.</hi> 10. See <hi>Bell. lib. 1. De miſſa. cap. 12</hi>
                  </note> the Godhead, the Soule or humane nature of man bee not ſeene as they are in themſelues: ſo likewiſe Chriſt in their doctrine may bee truly ſaide to bee ſeene, in the formes of bread and wine.</p>
               <p>And is it not a frequent ſaying with them, when Chriſt is caried in their Proceſſions, <hi>Spectate, Deus venit; Behould, God comes?</hi> And was it not a ſaying of ould, that they would aske of their Children, whether they had (reſpecting the eleuated Hoſt at Maſſe) ſeen God almigh tie vpon ſuch or ſuch a daie? And doth not <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſeeme to confeſſe, that Chriſt may as trulie be ſaid to bee ſeene in the formes of bread and wine, as the <hi>Angells</hi> are ſeen in ſuch formes and ſhapes as they take? yea hee brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>Saint Auſtines</hi> authoritie for the ſame, that young Infants, if they were not otherwiſe inſtructed (in reſpect of that which is tould them, concerning the diuine <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi>) would thinke that Chriſt did (when he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant vpon earth) appeare in the formes of bread and wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>2</label> Secondly I anſwer, touching Conuerſation; that the <hi>Pontificians</hi> cannot denie, but that for their parts there is a conuerſation betwixt themſelues and their Chriſt: for
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17710:30"/> they are preſentially with him, they ſee him, they handle him, they ſpeak to him, they adore him, they adorne
<note place="margin">A kind of true conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be twixt the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> and their Chriſt.</note> him, they lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k him vp, they carrie him about, they walk to him and with him, they watch with him and for him, they cloath him, and doe all ſeruices to him as to a Chriſt preſent, both knowing, ſeeing, and vnderſtanding well what they doe to him.</p>
               <p>And further, for their Chriſts part there preſent in
<note place="margin">A maine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon pretended for ſuch cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral preſence is, that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh faithfull may haue com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort thereby which cannot bee without ſome manner of conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. See <hi>Iacob. Suarez, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauro qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drageſ. ſer. 42. in fer. 3. do. pal.</hi>
                  </note> perſon, I hope they will not deny, but that hee knoweth himſelfe to be with them, and in what manner hee is with them; ſo that he heareth their prayers, ſeeth their geſtures, weareth their ornaments, worketh by his graces in their Soules, and doth oftentimes many miraculous and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious effects and Cures amongſt them. And, is not this a true manner of conuerſation of ſuch a Chriſt, with ſuch his Chriſtians? What is Conuerſation, but mutuall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe of Intelligent and vnderſtanding Perſons, in actions done with knowledge and vnderſtanding? They vnderſt and, what they doe to this their Chriſt: and I hope this their Chriſt knowes, heares and ſees, what is ſo done by them to him; and what anſwerably hee doeth to them. When I was in <hi>Rome,</hi> and pronounced an Oration, in the <hi>Roman</hi> Engliſh Church, vpon the burning and torturing of Maiſter Walter <hi>Marſh,</hi> that worthie <hi>Martyr;</hi> Amongſt other points, I remember one notable paſſage: to wit, That Chriſt beeing carried in a <hi>Pixe</hi> in that Proceſſion (where Maſter <hi>Marſh</hi> ſtrook it downe) by the handes of a <hi>Biſhop;</hi> their Oration taught mee thus to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay thereof
<note place="margin">See my <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeth and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiteth in their proceſſions.</note> in effect; to wit, that when Chriſt did viſit his faithfull, and make progreſſe amongſt them, then the impious and ſacrilegious hands of that wicked man did violently beate and caſt him downe. Lo then, here is a point of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular conuerſation; to wit, viſitation, and progreſſe, accknowledged in their Chriſt, when hee is carried about in their Proceſſions.</p>
               <p>If it be here obiected, that their Chriſt doth not ſpeake
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17710:31"/> vnto them with vocall words, or ſound of mouth; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That is but one point of conuerſation; and the ſame may bee ſupplied by ſignes, and ſome motions or geſtures, which the Prieſts make vpon him, and about him: aſwell as a certain Gentlewoman at <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> ſome
<note place="margin">Miſtris <hi>Brown,</hi> wife of maſter <hi>Iohn Brown,</hi> vncle to the now Lord <hi>Mountague.</hi> Maſter <hi>Manger</hi> the prieſt.</note> twelue years agoe, was wonted by ſignes to vnderſtand what ſins a dumb boy of hers had done; and ſo to make for him a confeſſion vnto the Prieſt, who vſually gaue thereupon abſolution to the boy. Howſoeuer it bee, if there want no other maner of conuerſation than ſpeech, it can onely be ſaid, that the conuerſation is lame and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue, and not that there is no conuerſation at all. And ſo I adjoin a third anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>3</label> Thirdly, I anſwer, that although ſome Readings haue, that theſe falſe Prophets teach Chriſt to be <hi>in penetralibus, in the penetrals,</hi> as the Vulgar; in <hi>Secrets,</hi> as others; in <hi>clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets,</hi> as the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> (in all which manner of places and ſecrets, the Papiſts doo teach Chriſt to bee) notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the Hebrew word vſed by <hi>Hutter</hi> in his Hebrew Teſtament, and the <hi>Syriack</hi> vſed by our Sauiour (as it may bee probably thought) and the <hi>Greek</hi> word, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſignifie a more ſecret place than cloſet or parlour; the very <hi>ſecret</hi> of the boſome; the <hi>Secret</hi> of a <hi>hutch, cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, ambry, arke, tabernacle, cheſt,</hi> or any ſuch like wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in victuals are put, and wherein treaſury is laid vp: into all which manners of <hi>Secrets</hi> and <hi>Penetrals</hi> (yea, into poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets ſomtimes) the Papiſts do put and place their Chriſt; ſaying, <hi>Behould, he is there, behould, he is heer;</hi> beleeue it, though it may ſeem to be neuer ſo admirable, and neuer ſo incredible. And ſuppoſe it be onely to be vnderſtood of cloſets (a word vſed by the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi>) I maruell what maner of conuerſation popiſh Dames will acknowledge may bee betwixt man and man in their <hi>cloſets.</hi> Surely, Chriſt may there be reputed to bee locked vp onely like a <hi>poenas,</hi> houſe God-ling, or like ſome delicious pot of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues</hi> or <hi>Preſerues.</hi> And ſo I ceaſe to adde any more, for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17710:31"/> the remouing of this firſt Obiection.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob∣iection. </seg>Second</label> A ſecond Obiection is made thus; that our Sauiour, in this prophecy, doth foretell of ſome <hi>falſe-prophets</hi> who ſhould denie him to be the true <hi>Meſsias,</hi> and ſhould teach another Chriſt, againſt him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> This obiection falleth eaſily, by all which I haue ſhewed and proued aboue, in my former reaſons; and is
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 10. &amp; 11</note> alſo refuted, by the ioynt conſent of all thoſe who doe apply this prophecy to all <hi>Schiſmatikes</hi> and <hi>Heretikes:</hi> all who, as they doe acknowledge Chriſt to bee the true <hi>Meſsias;</hi> ſo they pretend Chriſts ſpirituall preſence to bee ſpecially with them, and denie the ſame to all others. And ſurely, if theſe <hi>falſe-prophets</hi> and <hi>Pſeudo-Chriſts</hi> were to denie the Lord, and Giuer of life, <hi>Ieſus,</hi> I cannot ſee in <hi>what</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 24. 24. Not another Chriſt, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> true Chriſt, pretended to bee in <hi>Secrets.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>danger the elect ſhould bee, to bee ſeduced.</hi> For, if the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtian will haue in hate and abomination, them who ſhould teach another Chriſt; ſurely in a far more high degree the elect cannot but execrate the ſame. No, no: this <hi>pſeudo-chriſtaniſme</hi> is a <hi>myſterie of iniquitie.</hi> Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe muſt bee taught to be in <hi>Penetrals,</hi> that thereby <hi>the elect (if it were poſsible) might bee drawen,</hi> inſteed of the true Chriſt ſitting in the glory of his father, to worſhip a falſe Chriſt a vanity, a dreame, and a fancy, in the Secrets and Penetrals of bread, and wine: and ſo I adde a third Obiection, thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>3</label> Chriſt, in his prophecy, foretelleth of ſome <hi>Pſeudo-Chriſts</hi> and <hi>falſe-prophets,</hi> which were to come immediatly before his coming to Iudgement, and the conſummation of the world, &amp; to preach a preſence of Chriſt then &amp; at that time onely. Hee aymeth not therefore, in this place at the popiſh teaching of Chriſts beeing <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſecrets of their <hi>Church-Arks, Cupbords, tabernacles, Pixes &amp;c.</hi> for, this doctrine of theirs, hath beene a long time verie publike, at leaſt, ſince the Generall councell of
<note place="margin">Con. Latera. cap. Firmiter.</note> 
                  <hi>Laterane</hi> vnder <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3: for, then the doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> was firſt decreed, as an article of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17710:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:17710:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:17710:33"/> Catholicke faith. I anſwer; It being moſt certaine that this is a myſterie of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> it is alſo as certaine that the ſame was to endure for the whole time of his raigne. Now then it is moſt manifeſt, that the time of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Flouriſh and ruffe, was to begin at that time when the <hi>diuell was to bee let looſe:</hi> which letting looſe, muſt needes bee vpon the verie point, or about the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing of the <hi>thouſand yeares, for which the diuell was</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoca. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>to bee bound.</hi> Which thouſand yeres of the diuells binding (whether beginning at the time of Chriſts birth, or at the time of his paſſion, or for ſome time after when the <hi>Goſpel</hi> was more generally preached) moſt cleare it is, that at the period of the ſame 1000. yeares the <hi>Antichristian</hi> my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<note place="margin">Platina, in vita Syluest. 2. Benno card. in vit. Hildebr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>di.</note> did moſt powerfully worke in the daies (or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts) of <hi>Sylueſter</hi> the 2. a moſt notorious <hi>Antichriſt, a man of Sinne, and Son of perdition,</hi> if euer anie. And then alſo, and about that time, the <hi>myſterie</hi> of <hi>tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and conſequently of Chriſt beeing in hidden <hi>Secrets and Penetrals</hi> there to-bee ſeene, adored and worſhipped, did begin more generally to bee ſpred abroad, by <hi>falſe-Chriſts</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. ſub Nicol. 2. et ſub Greg. 7. Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frank, lb. de cor por. dom.</note> 
                  <hi>and falſe-prophets, to the ſeducing and peruerting of the greateſt part of the Church:</hi> and then were <hi>the Elect in greateſt danger to bee peruerted,</hi> when the whole Church (welnie) in the daies of the <hi>Lateran Councell</hi> did fall into this <hi>apoſtaſie and defection.</hi> Which being ſo, wee may not
<note place="margin">Conc. Lateran. cap. 1.</note> marueile, that this <hi>pſeudo-Chriſtaniſme</hi> doth continue, for the whole <hi>tunc</hi> and time of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> reigne, and the Antichriſtian empire.</p>
               <p>And although Chriſt ſeeme to ſome, to ſpeake of this
<note place="margin">This falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>secrets</hi> was to bee for long time in the world. Amanif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt proofe. Mat. 24. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſeudo-Chriſtianiſme, as</hi> though it were to happen immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atelie before his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to iudgement; yet moſt certaine it is, that this and moſt of thoſe things, which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour foretells in that chapter, are ſo implicately &amp; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtly deliuered, that the diſtinct and certaine times of diuers of them can hardly bee diſtinguiſhed. Onely this is moſt certaine, that (to vſe Chriſts phraſe) <hi>this Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:17710:33"/> (to weet, the ſtate of the Church from his firſt till his ſecond coming) <hi>ſhould not paſſe away vntill all things</hi> (there by him ſpoken) <hi>ſhould be fulfilled and accompliſhed:</hi> but for the certain ſeaſons when they were to bee accompliſhed, it is not there expreſſed. Again I anſwer, that all thoſe
<note place="margin">Rhemiſts on this place, <hi>Maldon. Ianſon,</hi> almoſt all.</note> (as many <hi>Pontificians</hi> doo) who apply this Prophecie to the priuate Conuenticles of Hereticks in any time or age of the Church, to the <hi>Donatiſts, Arrians, Pelagians, &amp;c.</hi> cannot reſtraine the ſame to the times that immediately precede the ſecond coming of Chriſt, and the conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world. And ſo I come to adjoine ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain obſeruations, moſt clearly confirming this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to bee fulfilled in the popiſh <hi>pſeudo-chriſtianiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt obſerue, that theſe <hi>falſe prophets were to doo manie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Firſt obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                  <hi>ſignes and wonders</hi> for the confirmation of this their falſe doctrine, Loe hee is in the <hi>penetrals. Dabunt ſigna magna, &amp;c. They ſhall giue great ſignes and wonders</hi> (ſaith Chriſt)
<note place="margin">Verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4</note> 
                  <hi>that, if it were poſſible, the very Elect ſhould be deceiued.</hi> And the Apoſtle pronounceth, that the coming of Antichriſt
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. 8</note> 
                  <hi>ſhould be by the operation of Satan, in all power of ſignes and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prodigies, and in all manner of wicked ſeducement of thoſe who periſh.</hi> All which how egregiouſly it is compleated in the Roman Antichriſtian Synagogue, <hi>Anthonie de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Ant. in ſum. hiſt. p. 3. tit. 24 c. 3. ¶. 2. Bell. lib. 3. de euch. cap. 8. Liber conform. Spec. mag. exem</hi> See <hi>Down. de Antichriſto. Paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h. l. de corp. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. c. 14. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbac. l. 7. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c. collat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 60. ſpec exem. verbo eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i.</hi>
                  </note> his hungry Aſſe leauing hay to goe worſhip Chriſt in the <hi>Secrets;</hi> the <hi>Aſſiſian Francis</hi> his <hi>Cade-Lamb</hi> adoring day by day the eleuated <hi>Hoſte</hi> at <hi>Maſſe;</hi> the kneeling of a black horſe with one knee onely before an Hoſte which was loſt (of one knee onely, becauſe the diuell was in the ſaid black horſe) <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> the Prieſt his ſeeing vpon the altar Chriſt in the form of a little childe, with many ſuch like prodigious vanities related by popiſh Authours, doo moſt manifeſtly euince. The Papiſts glory, that they haue miracles and ſignes for the confirmation of this their <hi>pſeudo-christianiſme;</hi> but this glory is their confuſion; for, if they had not miracles and prodigies for confirmation of the ſame, they ſhould not be thoſe falſe Prophets who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17710:34"/> our Sauiour heer fore-ſpeaketh of, <hi>that they ſhould do great ſignes and wonders, euen to the ſeducing of the Elect if it were poſſible.</hi> The ſignes of them therefore were to bee great, powerfull, many: we deny them not, nor them the glory therof.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>2</label> Secondly I obſerue, that theſe <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> were, by the meanes of this their falſe doctrine, <hi>to ſeduce many. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducent multos,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>They ſhall ſeduce many.</hi> Which
<note place="margin">Mat. 24. 11</note> wee ſee ſo fully accompliſhed in the Roman Synagogue, that <hi>the very Elect are in great danger and hazard to bee led</hi>
                  <note place="margin">If all be to bee ſeduced but the Elect (of which there is but a ſmall nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) what mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that there is ſuch a generall Apoſtaſie.</note> 
                  <hi>away by their ſo powerfull perſwaſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no one point which doth more ſtrongly hold and tie the diſciples of the Pope to him and his errours, than this myſterie, <hi>Behould, he is in the penetrals;</hi> Behold, we haue Chriſt perſonally and ſubſtantially in the Secrets of our Sacrament. For this cauſe, if we ſeek to draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one of them from that popiſh confuſion of errours, and <hi>Chaos</hi> of ſuperſtitions wherein they ſleep, what doo they moſt commonly alleage for their not-yeelding? Mary, this: You, you (ſay they) the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from vs the true and corporall preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament, and would feed vs with <hi>tropes, ſignes</hi> and <hi>figures</hi> onely: how then can or ſhall wee forſake true Chriſt, and come to feed on your husks of bread &amp; wine, which you onely haue? Wherein they doo egregiouſly calumniate vs: for, concerning <hi>rem ſacramenti, the thing of the Sacrament,</hi> and the vertue thereof, and the real con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction by grace and faith to Chriſt, wee teach it moſt conſtantly, and teach alſo a reall preſence of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (like that of Angels, which are in place by operation)
<note place="margin">Calu. in c. 26 Mat. B. Bilſon, part. 4. p. 728 729</note> by the means of the reall operation, and effectuall effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of grace by the ſame, working by faith and loue in the hearts of the faithfull receiuers.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruatiō </seg>3</label> I obſerue thirdly, that theſe falſe Prophets were not onely to ſeduce by ſweet perſwaſions, ſignes, wonders; but that alſo they were to adde great afflictions and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17710:34"/> to enforce the ſame: for, ſo much importeth the Saying of our Sauiour; who, preſently after his Charge, <hi>Go not ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, beleeue it not,</hi> mentioneth tribulation, ſaying; <hi>After the tribulation of thoſe daies.</hi> Whereby he inſtructeth his Faithfull, that the <hi>Elect,</hi> who would not be drawn to worſhip their pretended Chriſt in <hi>ſecrets, cloſets, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arks, cup-boards, tabernacles, &amp;c.</hi> ſhould for the ſame ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain great tribulations. The which how egregiouſly it hath been compleated by the Romaniſts, their perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all times and ages, ſince their generall Councell of
<note place="margin">Con. Lat. c. 3</note> 
                  <hi>Lateran,</hi> where the ſame falſe doctrine was vniuerſally decreed with an <hi>Anatheme</hi> &amp; curſe againſt all that ſhould deny the ſame, doth more than manifeſtly euince.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>4</label> In the fourth place I obſerue, out of the manner of our Sauiours Prophecy, that theſe falſe Prophets were at one and the ſame time to teach him to bee in ſundry Secrets: the which as it was neuer done by any other; ſo it is moſt punctually actuated by them; who at the ſelfe ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doo proclaim and teach, <hi>Lo, he is heer</hi> at <hi>Bruxels, he</hi>
                  <note place="margin">If this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy bee not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fild in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh church, let it be ſhewed where or in what time it hath been or may be more likely fulfilled.</note> 
                  <hi>is there</hi> at <hi>Mechlines,</hi> he is there at <hi>Rome,</hi> he is heer at <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos,</hi> he is heer at <hi>Naples,</hi> he is there vpon a horſe-back, he is heer in a lockt cloſet, hee is heer vpon this altar, hee is yonder vpon another altar, and where not? Which my obſeruation is more confirmed, if it bee conſidered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that our Sauiour ſpeaking of the <hi>Secrets,</hi> vſeth the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall number, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the Secrets, in the Penetrals. Speciallizing and nominating alſo theſe ſecret places wherein theſe falſe Prophets ſhould teach him to be, hee neuer nameth city, town or countrey, or any place fit for conuerſation; but only <hi>Secrets, Penetrals,</hi> that is (as I haue proued) <hi>boxes, cup-boards, arks, tabernacles, cheſts, cloſets,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Again: all the ſhewing of this pretended Chriſt that is done, was to be accompliſhed and performed, by the falſe Prophets and falſe Prieſts themſelues: and euen ſo it is acted in the Roman Church. Further: theſe were to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17710:35"/> the knowne, publike, viſible Church, all but the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect:</hi> wherein the Romaniſts doo moſt reioicingly &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphingly build and reſt themſelues, to the high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all others.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation </seg>Laſt</label> Laſtly, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firm this my interpretation of theſe words, I adde thus out of the Prophet <hi>Daniel:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 11. 38 39</note> There wee may reade, that Antichriſt ſhould <hi>for ſake the God of his Fathers, and with gold and ſiluer ſhould worſhip the god Maozim.</hi> Now <hi>Maozim,</hi> according to the interpretation of the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedeſt, hath a double ſignification in it; to weet, <hi>Summi roboris, &amp; inhabitatio tabernaculi; Of greateſt ſtrength, and the inhabitation or in-dwelling in a tabernacle.</hi> Which doth ſo liuely point vnto vs the pſeudo-Chriſt of the Papiſts, whom they pretend to be Chriſt himſelf (<hi>God</hi> indeed of greateſt ſtrength, and the <hi>power</hi> of his Father) and whom alſo they profeſſe to dwell in their <hi>Church-tabernacles,</hi> that nothing can bee brought clearer againſt them, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with better purpoſe to confirm the interpretation of this our Text which we haue in hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who laboureth ſtoutly to free his holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 3. de rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ont. c. 14</note> from worſhipping the god <hi>Maozim,</hi> in his beſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thinketh (citing <hi>Lyra</hi>'s authority for the ſame) that <hi>Maozim</hi> ſignifieth <hi>fortitude, or of greateſt ſtrength, and a tower withall;</hi> ſo that the god <hi>Maozim</hi> is in his interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>The God of greatest fortitude in a towre:</hi> And if <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> in ſtead of the word <hi>towre,</hi> had vſed the word <hi>turret,</hi> then he had hit the mark, and mentioned thoſe very <hi>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets</hi> which the Papiſts vſe to bear their god <hi>Maozim</hi> in, vp
<note place="margin">An Hoſte pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, being too great for the turret wherein it was to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Doc. Cyp. tratta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o de la miſſa. page 428</hi>
                  </note> and down in their Proceſſions. Such a manner of <hi>turret</hi> was that which was vſed at <hi>Barcelone</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> when the Inquiſitor <hi>Molon</hi> was enforced to round and leſſen (with a pair of ſciſſers) a conſecrated <hi>Hoste</hi> which was to bee put into the ſame pixe or turret: but, it beeing too great for the turret, till the Hoſte was leſſened, the Proceſſion was ſtaid, and could not proceed. Some ſuch like thing hapned at <hi>Rome</hi> in my time in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, when
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17710:35"/> the Proceſſion was ſtaid, and could not goe forth at the time appointed, becauſe he who ſang the high Maſſe (as
<note place="margin">A ſecond maſs ſaid to prouide an Hoſt fit for the pix or tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, at the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh colledge at Rome.</note> they call it) that day, had forgotten to make a conſecrated <hi>Hoſte</hi> fit for the <hi>pix</hi> and <hi>turret</hi> wherein it was to be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp and down in Proceſſion. And ſo I end this point; inferring out of all that which hath been prooued, that the <hi>falſe Prophets, pſeudo-Chriſts,</hi> and <hi>falſe Anointed-ones,</hi> of the popiſh Church do directly and punctually teach and preach Chriſt to bee vp and down, <hi>heer and there</hi> in the <hi>Secrets and Penetrals</hi> of their Church-arks and taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles; the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the very Secrets at which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour heer aimeth, and giueth his moſt ſtrict charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame, <hi>Beleeue it not,</hi> beleeue it not. Which charge of Chriſt is our third part: and now in a few words we come to declare the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Beleeue it not.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">part </seg>The third</label> Admirable is the goodnes of Chriſt, to fore-warn his <hi>Elect</hi> of dangers which they are to auoid. Hee it is who worketh in His, all in all, <hi>to begin and perfect,</hi> to deſire and perform, to purpoſe and to doo: yet he doth it not in vs without vs, who notwithſtanding can do nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him. For this reſpect hee ſaith, <hi>Beleeue it not, Goe not out, Beleeue it not.</hi> But, whil'ſt our Sauiour in this place doth fore-charge his Faithfull, that they beleeue it not, we muſt not ſo interpret the ſame, as though with the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall act or habit of faith the ſame may bee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; no, no: errour, and ſo pernicious an errour as this is, may not be the object of faith. Whereas therefore he chargeth, <hi>Beleeue it not,</hi> we are thus to take the ſame; that by no means wee be perſwaded of the truth of it, but that wee take it (as it is) for a moſt pernicious and damnable errour, and a higheſt point of impiety. <hi>Beleeue it not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The falſe Prophets ſay, <hi>Behould</hi> this admirable myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and beleeue it; Beleeue that Chriſt is perſonally <hi>totus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Miſſ. rom ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>que. Breu. rom. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. corp. chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ym.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ub vtra<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſpecie, wholly vnder the Secrets of both forms:</hi> but, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Beleeue it not.</hi> They ſay, <hi>Praeſtet fides ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17710:36"/> ſenſuum defectui: let faith ſupply the defect of the ſenſes;</hi> beleeue it: Chriſt ſaith, Theſe falſe Prophets and pſeudo-Chriſts ſhall indeed ſo ſay, but <hi>Beleeue it not.</hi> O how preſumptuous is that man who will beleeue anie thing of Chriſt which he hath not commanded or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to be beleeued of him! but more then deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſumptuous then is he who (to vſe Saint <hi>Austines</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de vnit. eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. c. 10</note> words in like caſe) <hi>will beleeue ought contra vocem paſtoris tam apertam, tam claram &amp;c. againſt the voice of the ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard ſo clear, ſo manifeſt: the which, no man is ſo dull that he can iuſtly ſay, he hath not vnderſtood it;</hi> yea, and this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſhep-herds voice condemning a point of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt errour, ſo prodigious and ſo paradoxicall, that few of the profeſſers of Popery it ſelf doo conſtantly beleeue the ſame.</p>
               <p>And ſo heer, vpon this occaſion, I cannot omit to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<note place="margin">Three ſorts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>opiſh profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers.</note> vnto you what I haue by moſt certain experience (concerning this point) obſerued amongſt them. I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh all the profeſſers of Popery into three degrees: Firſt, <hi>Atheiſts</hi> or <hi>ſemi-Atheiſts;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>zelantes, ſed pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uae vitae, zealous papists,</hi> but of wicked liues; thirdly, <hi>zelan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſed ſimplicis vitae, zealous papiſts, but of more honeſt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations and liues.</hi> The firſt (whereof Italie and France is very full) by their irreligious carriage at their Maſſes, tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with and courting of dames then and there, their adoring of the eleuated Hoſte but with one knee, or with the ſparing and ſhort congie of their bodies, or with a few ſhort knocks vpon their breaſts, doe euince, that they do not beleeue Chriſt to bee there perſonally, eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp in the hands of the Prieſt.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort, <hi>zealous</hi> but of wicked liues, do ſeem moſt conſtantly to be perſwaded of the ſame, and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed euer with great violence carried and bent againſt all ſuch who beleeue it not. I could be particular.</p>
               <p>The third ſort, the more diſcreet Papiſt, doth indeed
<note place="margin">Popiſh profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of more honeſt &amp; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt faith of Chriſt in their maſſe or boxes</note> endeauour to beleeue it, and is much perplexed that hee
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17710:36"/> or ſhee can not conſtantly beleeue it: but fewe or none there are of this kinde, who are not daie by daie moleſted with thoughts (of <hi>misbeleefe</hi> or <hi>vnbeleefe,</hi> as they call it) that Chriſt is not truely and perſonally in the <hi>Secrets</hi> and <hi>Penetrals</hi> of bread and wine; wherefore they pray &amp; they crie daie &amp; night, <hi>Lord helpe our beleefe. So they ſerue a God,</hi> on whom conſtantly they cannot beleeue, &amp; <hi>who giueth them no reſt, neither by date, nor by night.</hi> How true this is I
<note place="margin">Ie rem. 16. 13.</note> will not endeuour to confirme by particulars; it is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of the <hi>Myſterie of iniq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itie:</hi> but, that this is moſt true, I referre me to the conſciences of the beſt and moſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts</hi> themſelues; and to thoſe who hearing and taking the <hi>Confeſsions</hi> of their flocke, doe wel vnderſtand with what daily and inceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant doubts, feares,
<note place="margin">The papiſts moſt immane; burning others for denying that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which the moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous amongſt them doe not conſtantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</note> ſcrupuloſities, they are miſerably vexed, afflicted, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented So is then the caſe; the verie beſt of the Popiſh Church are not conſtantly perſwaded of the truth of that, for the not beleeuing of which, they haue moſt in humanely (in their fierie trialls) taken away and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to aſhes the beſt of our churches, the Saints and ſeruants of God, who haue offered themſelues to their furies <hi>for the teſtimonie of Ieſus; Beleeue it not.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Beleeue it not.</head>
               <p>Moſt Religious Audience, if my voice were a ſhrill trumpet, ſufficient to ſounde in the eares of all within this <hi>Brittiſh Monarchie,</hi> I ſhould ſay vnto them, warranted thereunto by Chriſts charge, <hi>beleeue it not though an Angell from heauen,</hi> though al the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntifician falſe-prophets</hi> cry out, <hi>loe he is here in the Cloſet</hi> of this Lady (as the vſe is) <hi>loe he is there</hi> (in the cellar of that Marchant (as the manner is) <hi>loe hee is yonder</hi> in the treaſurie boxes of that Grandy (as the cuſtome hath beene and may bee) <hi>beleeue it not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it not.</hi> It is the Lords charge, worthy of all receiuing: it is the Lords charge neceſſarily to bee receiued, vnleſſe wee will be ſeduced and drawen away, to the eternall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of our Soules. <hi>Beleeue it not</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Beleeue
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17710:37"/> it not.</hi> And doth hee not in this charge ſeeme thus to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort and charge his Faithfull? My firſt and Prime com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> is, <hi>Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods but me:</hi> but if you beleeue <hi>theſe falſe-prophets,</hi> then ſhall you worſhip another God for mee; howſoeuer they falſely pretend that they haue mee, and no other ſubſtantially and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in their <hi>Secrets</hi> there to be worſhipped and adored, but mee; but <hi>beleeue it not.</hi> I ſay, another God for mee; <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> for mee; according to thoſe blaſphemous ould verſes, ſometimes frequent in the Antichriſtian Synagogue;
<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lcot. in 4. q. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conſtat, in altari carnem de pane creari.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hic panis deus eſt, Qui negat hoc, reus eſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Bread, is made the fleſh of Chriſt.</l>
                  <l>This bread is God. Say <hi>no,</hi> thou ly'ſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>You profeſſe in your <hi>Creed,</hi> that I am <hi>aſcended vp into</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act. 3. Auguſt. Tract.</hi> 50. in <hi>Ioan. et epiſt ad Dardanum.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>heauen, &amp; ſit there at the right hand of my Father in his Glorie; wherein the heauens ſhall recceiue mee</hi> vntill my comming: but, if you beleeue theſe <hi>falſe-prophets,</hi> you will alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue mee to bee in <hi>the ſecrets</hi> of <hi>Arks, Pixes,</hi> and <hi>Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſts vnion with his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, though Spirituall.</note> where neither I ſhall nor will be. For, <hi>Cui bono?</hi> to what end? whereas the ſumme of that communion and coniunction, which is betwixt mee and mine, is Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall in the Soule &amp; Spirit; for the effecting wherof what neede a corporall and carnall preſence? Therefore <hi>beleeue it not.</hi> Againe: this <hi>Sacrament is a</hi> ſacred, ſignificant and working ſigne: it is a remembrance &amp; <hi>a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me:</hi> How then I in it, perſonally? <hi>Beleeue it not.</hi> It is indeede a
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>communication of my bodie;</hi> but, in eating of ſanctified bread. It is a <hi>participation of my blood;</hi> but, in drinking of the hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<note place="margin">God-chriſt made preſent in the Secrets by theſe falſe prophets. <hi>Bellar. lib. 3. de Euchariſt. cap. 18.</hi>
                  </note> and bleſſed wine. But, theſe <hi>falſe prophets</hi> teach a <hi>tranſubſtantiating</hi> of bread into mee, of wine into me. Yea, they dare thus blaſpheme, that <hi>Creatura est factor creatoris ſui, the Creature is the maker of his Creatour.</hi> So then God muſt bee behoulding to man, for his making (ſo ſom call it) for his creating (ſo others) for his production
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17710:37"/> (ſo ſome) for his adduction and bringing: ſo with <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmien</hi> others tearme it; <hi>but beleeue them not; beleeue it not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly: if you beleeue it, then you put your truſt in it, and on it, you long after it, and adhaere to it: then <hi>not ſurſum, but deorſum corda, quaquaverſum corda; then will not your hearts be lift vpward, but caſt downe, or diſperſed vp &amp; downe, here, and there, euerie-where,</hi> where they pretend me to bee; whereas <hi>venerable Antiquitie</hi> cryed out in the very ſacredſt of theſe <hi>myſteries, Surſum corda, ſurſum corda, let vs lift vp, let vs lift vp our hearts;</hi> and the People of God euer anſwered, <hi>Habemus ad dominum,</hi> wee haue them, wee lift them vp vnto the Lord, wee are not <hi>humbly nor meanly intentiue to that which is ſet vpon the table; but wee lift vp our hearts vnto the Lord who ſitteth aboue in the Heauens, donec finiantur ſecula, vntill the conſummation of all generations and ages.</hi> I conclude and ſumme vp all in this ſhort prayer; Dear Sauiour, as thou haſt ben graciouſly pleaſed to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne vs that we beleeue it not: ſo bee thou as graciouſly pleaſed to ſtrengthen and confirme vs that wee beleeue it not. <hi>Bleſsing, Clarity, Wiſedome, Thankeſgiuing, Honour, Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> to our <hi>God, together with the Lambe (that</hi> lurketh not in popiſh ſecrets, <hi>but ſitteth on the Throne) and to the euer-bleſſed Spirit, bee rendered by vs, and all creature<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, from hence-forth and for euer,</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Deo vni, trino<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
